<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Camino-2008 | Kevin Trowbridge]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/blog/categories/camino-2008/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-29T15:53:50-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kevin Trowbridge]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[kevinmtrowbridge@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crossing the Pyrenees]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2008-10-24-crossing-the-pyrenees"/>
    <updated>2008-10-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/crossing-the-pyrenees</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[After about 7 days of walking in France, I arrived in St. Jean Pied-de-Port, which is the last French town before the 
Pyrenees and the border with Spain.

I passed through about 11am, which allowed me to experience the town shutting down for a few hours for lunch, which I 
can only assume is a French example of a Spanish style siesta.

![st jean street][1]

_The main street of St. Jean Pied-de-Port, looking back while heading out of town to the south._

Once I headed out of town, the trail started climbing steeply.  By about 3pm, I was huffing and puffing like a 
locomotive, but I was rewarded with quite simply, stunning views:

![pyrenees 1][2]

_A view down into France from about 1/3rd of the way up the Pyrenees._

Lots of people have the idea that you must walk the entire 28 kilometers from St. Jean through to Roncesvalles in Spain, 
all in one day.  Luckily that is not true and I was able to spend the night about 1/2 way, at the Auberge Orisson.
It's a really beautiful place located far up into the mountains, with a beautiful patio that has a spectacular view.
That night I met several folks who I would be walking with for the next several days.

Karen, an Irish lass, with whom I would later 'paint Pamplona red' ( we met a bunch of locals and kept shutting down 
bars and migrating to the next, finishing around 3am ;):

![karen][3]

_Karen at the Auberge Orisson._

And Mickey and Peter, two American brothers-in-law who were doing the walk together to see if they could forge a 
relationship despite their differences (Mickey is from the south, a Florida republican with a provocative streak, and 
Peter is a good northern boy from Minnesota.)

We stayed up late at Orisson hanging out on the patio and looking at the stars.  Then the next morning, a spectacular 
dawn greeted us and it was time to go walk over the mountains!

![sunrise][4]

_A beautiful Pyrenee sunrise._

About the crossing itself, I wrote to Meg just after we arrived in Roncesvalles:

> The walk was pretty spectacular in fact, I left very early just as the sun was rising. It was a perfect dawn and the 
> clouds were pink and golden colored. There was a VERY strong wind and we kept walking up and up … the pass was around 
> 4500 feet, so it was a little like walking up Mt. Diablo.
> 
> The trees stopped after a while … we passed the border into Spain which was almost completely unmarked, just  an old 
> fence and a stone marker that said: &#8216;199&#8217;
> 
> At the very top you could see down into France and down into Spain. It was very beautiful. Today was quite special and 
> I am very happy to have done it.

![virge dorisson self portrait][5]

_Me, near the Vierge d&#8217;Orisson, about 3/4 of the way to the top of the pass. You can tell how strong the wind was from 
my hair!_

[1]: /assets//st_jean_street.jpg
[2]: /assets//pyrenees_1.jpg
[3]: /assets//karen.jpg
[4]: /assets//sunrise.jpg
[5]: /assets//virge_dorisson_self_portrait.jpg]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Le Puy Trail]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2008-10-14-the-le-puy-trail"/>
    <updated>2008-10-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/the-le-puy-trail</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[The main trail that comes down through France is called the 'Le puy' trail---named for its origin city, 'Le Puy,' 
France. It's about 800 km long as well, so if one were to hike from Le Puy (and many do), it would be about 1600km.

![pyrenees from plane][1]

_View down into the Pyrenees on the Madrid-Toulouse flight. I climbed over these mountains!!_

Since I studied France in college and my French is actually quite good (I always have loved languages), I wanted to hike 
part of this trail. I chose a city more or less randomly, about a week from the border, 'Aire-sur-l'Adour'---and based my 
plans on starting there. On Oct. 1st I flew from SF, arriving in Toulouse on Oct. 2nd. I wandered around Toulouse in a 
bit of a daze, got rained on and pretty cold, and wondered why I earth, I ever wanted to do this ridiculous walk! ;)

In this emotionally weak state, I hunted around in my pack for my French language guide to the 'Le Puy' trail, 
charmingly called '[Miam Miam Dodo][2]' (which means: 'Yumm yumm, sleep sleep', or more prosaically, 
'Eating and Sleeping'), and started calling various hostels in Aire-sur-l'Adour. The phone was answered by a very nice 
lady who seemed to feel my pain. Yes, they were open. Yes, there were other pilgrims, I would not be all alone. Was the 
rainy weather typical? Not very, it was the first time it had rained in two weeks.

![toulouse cathedral][3]

_The Toulouse cathedral as seen from the street._

![rainy self portrait][4]

_It was rainy and depressing in Toulouse._

I got on a bus from Toulouse to Aire-sur-l'Adour and we sped away, the driver careening out through the suburbs of 
Toulouse and into the countryside. I tried to sleep but was not particularly successful. The bus was full of rural 
French folks, poorer types. Mothers with children, immigrants, workers.

![french bus][5]

_French regional bus that took me from Toulouse to Aire-sur-l'Adour._

At 7pm, it was dark, raining, and the bus dropped me off basically on the side of the road. I chose a direction again, 
more or less at random, and started walking. After a few minutes, I crossed the 'Adour' river, and came into a square. 
There were a few men in a cafe, but I didn't feel up to asking them how to find the hostel, so I kept walking. I came 
upon the cathedral. A man walked by, walking his dog. 'Are you a pilgrim?' he asked. He shook my hand and said that he, 
too, had done the walk. He led me through the dark, empty streets and pointed up a hill. "It's about five minutes walk 
up there, on the right."

I walked into the albergue. It was full of people. One man was getting his feet treated for blisters. "Where have you 
come from?" They asked me. They thought that I had come in from walking that day, and did not realize that I had just 
essentially gotten off the plane. They were quite welcoming, gave me some of the meal they had prepared, and a ton of 
wine.

![first albergue][6]

_The couple that ran the albergue. It was a private albergue, as distinguished from the municipal ones. The husband had 
walked the entire trail (Le Puy---Santiago) 7 times!_

![imri][7]

_Imri Amiel, a young Isralien who was on his own version of the pilgrimage, walking to the small French town where his 
father was hidden from the Germans during WWII._

![phillipe and andrea][8]

_Phillipe (A Frenchman who had left his job.) and Andrea (German, had walked from her home in Bern, Switzerland together 
with her husband)._

[2]: http://www.amazon.fr/Miam-miam-dodo-Compostelle-Puy-en-Velay-Saint-Jean-Pied-Port/dp/2916446109/ref=pd_bxgy_b_text_b/171-4719513-0558649

[1]: /assets//pyrenees_from_plane.jpg
[3]: /assets//toulouse_cathedral.jpg
[4]: /assets//rainy_self_portrait.jpg
[5]: /assets//french_bus.jpg
[6]: /assets//first_albergue.jpg
[7]: /assets//imri.jpg
[8]: /assets//phillipe_and_andrea.jpg]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aire-sur-l'Adour to Arzacq-Arraziguet]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2008-10-14-aire-sur-ladour-to-arzacq-arraziguet"/>
    <updated>2008-10-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/aire-sur-ladour-to-arzacq-arraziguet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Unfortunately there is much more to write than I have the appetite (or time) for!  I will have to try to catch up later.

The first few days of walking were quite hard.  At the end of the first day, I wrote to Meg (using the iPhone, more on 
that later):

> I was standing in the cabine telephonique five minutes ago trying to call you … but having some issues with the old 
> telephone card … and extremely tired / freezing from the autumn weather here, so decided to write you an email instead. 
> Tomorrow night (ie around 9-12 am PST) I will make a bigger effort with the telephone.
>
> Suffice it to say that I am quite happy, experiencing a volcano of socialability here in the olde EU… ;) In a real 
> small and cute French town … soo tired though!! Holy crap. I will sleep like a freaking baby.
>
> It rained today (but only for a few hours) and we walked 30km which is plenty far&#8212;the French part of the camino does 
> not have as many historic sites as the Spanish part … but it seems to have quite good accomadations and there are a 
> surprising # of pilgrims considering the time of year.

The churches in France have not been well maintained.  When I visted Mathieu in Bourges, we went to see the cathedral 
there&#8212;which is huge&#8212;one of the most interesting things about it, I thought, was that all of the statues had been 
left in their post-French-revolution state, that is to say&#8212;they had all had their heads chopped off.  So you saw the 
typhanum of the cathedral with a bunch of headless statues.  So&#8212;in terms of the history of France and Spain, France s
tripped the church of the majority of its possessions and power at the time of the revolution, that is, 1792, whereas 
in Spain, the church retained / retains much more power, and folks are more religious in general.  For example, tonight 
here in Pamploma at 7:30 the church bells rang and the streets were full of older folks walking to the cathedral for 
mass.  This has a direct effect on the quality of the art / preservation of the churches you see along the route.
Anyways, that is my theory.  I suppose it must be more complicated than that, since there are some beautiful and well 
maintained churches in France, but I would wager the theory would hold up en gross.

![pimbo portal][1]

_The facade of the church of the church in Pimbo._
 
As we can see, it&#8217;s in quite poor shape. The statues are missing from 
the tympanum and the archivolt seems to have been disassembled and reassembled at some point, as it is inconsistent: 
there are plain blocks, blocks with geometric shapes, and a small section that contains figures.

Here is a detail photo of the small figures you see at the top of the rightmost column:

![detail decayed column][2]

_Detail of surviving figures on capital of column of Pimbo&#8217;s church._

Pimbo had other attractions though, a beautiful albergue with a very nice hostess who welcomed us and served us coffee.
It is somehow a heavenly experience, to be practically dead from 10 miles of walking, and then to stagger into the most 
convivial little room with posters, chairs, a cat, and a charming lady who serves you coffee and questions you about 
your experience.

![pimbo hostess][3]

_The auberge hostess at Pimbo who served us coffee and made very pleasant conversation._

Here is Andrea with the auberge&#8217;s cat&#8212;they had worked out a compromise on the seating arrangement.

![andrea and_cat][4]

_Cats make good company._

Later that evening we came into Arzacq-Arraziguet, got our first view of the Pyrenees in the distance, and ate a very 
nice meal with the other pilgrims.  I was surprised by how many there were, perhaps 20-30…

Our first view of the Pyrenees:

![pyrenees first view][5]

_The first view of the Pyrenees in the distance._

[1]: /assets//pimbo_portal.jpg
[2]: /assets//detail_decayed_column.jpg
[3]: /assets//pimbo_hostess.jpg
[4]: /assets//andrea_and_cat.jpg
[5]: /assets//pyrenees_first_view.jpg]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Map]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2008-10-14-a-map"/>
    <updated>2008-10-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/a-map</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[After approximately 10 days and  230 kilometers (or 142 miles) of walking, I am in Pamplona!

Dan asked if I could post a map, 'a la Indiana Jones movies' of where I have been and where I am now, so I have done my 
best with 'Paint' on this cafe computer ... sorry it is a bit crude but more effective I think, than no map at all, and 
gives everyone an idea of where the Camino de Santiago passes, and where I have been, and where my destination is:

![ways of st james in europe][1]

So just to explain ... you're looking at a map of southwestern France and northern Spain.  There are many lines of the 
map, because there is more than one historic pilgrimage route.  During the middle ages, pilgrims came from all over 
Europe (from their front porch), as they say here.  Especially many French came, so the routes converged (more or less) 
to cross over the Pyrenee mountains at the border from France to spain.  And so there is one main route, called the 
'Camino Frances' or the 'French road,' across northern Spain.  That is the thick red line crossing northern Spain.

I colored my own trail in a slightly more radioactive color of red, we can call it 'Microsoft red.'  ;)  I started 
walking in Aire-sur-l'Adour, France, on October 3rd, and arrived in Pamplona, Spain, yesterday, October 13th.

Tomorrow I continue walking on towards Santiago tomorrow.  There are about 700 kilometers left to go, or 437 miles.  I 
should arrive there in about a month!

[1]: /assets//ways_of_st_james_in_europe.png]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lots to Say!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2008-10-07-lots-to-say"/>
    <updated>2008-10-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/lots-to-say</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[So, let's see, I have been walking for five days now.  I am still alive and more or less sane, so that is good.

It's ironic that I normally have hours per day on the internet, when I have nothing in particular to write about, 
whereas now, I have a million stories to write, but not necessarily that much time to write.

So, hiking in Europe goes something like this, as far as I can tell.  You have your pack, but you don't carry all that 
much---just your clothes, a sleeping bag, aiming for about 15 pounds.  You buy all of your food from restaurants and 
stores that you pass by.  You walk about 10-20 miles per day.  At the end of the day, there is some sort of socialistic 
enterprise (a building constructed by the state for walkers to stay in, someone's house to whom you pay 20ish dollars to 
be able to eat with them, shower, sleep ...) to allow you to sleep.

Tonight is the most interesting place I have yet experienced---it's a house run by young people ... apparently the income 
from the house is meant to be put to use helping poor young people in the area ...  I wonder if it will work given that 
the pilgrims are pretty poor themselves.  It seems like selling Armstrong armbands for 5 dollars apiece is a more 
ingenious way of creating money out of nothing, but I digress.)  Anyways the effect is of living with a bunch of French 
hippies!  What could be better?  They are listening to jazz and taking 5 hours to cook me eccentric middle eastern 
food!  ;)

Anyways, here are some pictures.  I shouldn't spend all night on the computer here, I think in two days I will be in St 
Jean Pied de Port and will be able to pay for a private computer where I can spend a decent amount of time writing 
something worthy. 

Meanwhile here are some pictures:

![The hills are alive with the sound of music!][1]

![Some of my walking companions][2]

[1]: /assets//sound_of_music.jpg
[2]: /assets//walking_companions.jpg]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
