<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Camino-2006 | Kevin Trowbridge]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/blog/categories/camino-2006/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-03T12:12:42-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kevin Trowbridge]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[kevinmtrowbridge@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some Photos From the Camino De Santiago, 2006]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2006-08-02-some-photos-from-santiago-de-compostela"/>
    <updated>2006-08-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/some-photos-from-santiago-de-compostela</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Photos are tricking in. Here are some that Louise sent me ...

The figure on the road sign appeared regularly alongside the route. We called him Michael Jackson because Louise pointed 
out that he seemed to be slapping his derriere. The concrete marker is an example of the type found along the entire 
trail. They appear several times per kilometer (at intersections or points of confusion, and usually include the number 
of kilometers left to Santiago).

![michael the european tour](/assets//michael-the-european-tour.jpg "We called him Michael Jackson 
because Louise pointed out that he seemed to be slapping his derriere.")

Louise is a graphic designer from South Africa and one of the few Anglophone girls we met. She was quite clever and 
energetic so it was love at first sight.

![nineteen-hundred hours](/assets//19h00.jpg "She was quite clever and energetic so it was love at 
first sight.")
 
Louise and I went drunkenly into a shop at midnight and bought cigarettes from an infinitely patient old lady. It seemed 
quite different from the sort of thing we would be doing at home, so we laughed and had my brother take a picture of us 
drinking in a shop. You can see us flaunting the cups of wine we carried indiscreetly into that commercial establishment.

![portomarin-kl](/assets//portomarin-kl.jpg "You can see us flaunting the cups of wine we carried 
indiscreetly into that commercial establishment.")

The Camino crosses a river here over a bridge that is 1500 years old. It is called 'Puente Ribadiso', which the ancient 
pilgrims used to rhymingly pun as 'Puente Paradiso' – it is a very pleasant spot and a group of young pilgrims are 
playing a game of polylinguistic volleyball in the river.

![puente-de-paradiso](/assets//puente-de-paradiso.jpg "It is called 'Puente Ribadiso', which the 
ancient pilgrims used to rhymingly pun as 'Puente Paradiso' – it is a very pleasant spot.")

The façade of the cathedral in Santiago de Compostela. This cathedral supposedly contains the remains of James, 4th apostle to Christ.

![santiago-016](/assets//santiago-016.jpg "This cathedral supposedly contains the remains of James, 
4th apostle to Christ.")
 
My hippie brother with a German girl who walked from her house (+3 months of walking time)! They are sitting in the 
plaza in front of the cathedral

![ja](/assets//ja.jpg "My hippie brother with a German girl who walked from her house (+3 months of 
walking time)!")
 
The couple in purple and blue are two quite young Germans. They are 19 years old, and chose a long distance walk 
(ie purgatory) for their vacation. Very commendable. They taught Jas some German.

![santiago-017](/assets//santiago-017.jpg "They chose a long distance walk (ie purgatory) for their 
vacation.")]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Night Trains, Madrid, and Flying Home]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2006-07-30-night-trains-madrid-and-flying-home"/>
    <updated>2006-07-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/night-trains-madrid-and-flying-home</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[## Night Trains

We left Santiago last Thursday at 10:30 on an overnight train. We had wonderful overnight berths---beds on a train. You 
share the compartment with three other folks, two sets of bunkbeds. Before Jas and I went to bed, we walked down to the 
restaurant car for a few final beers. Each country in Europe has its own trains; the trains in Spain seem a bit more 
popular (common): in the restaurant car the menu was printed above the bar in a jaunty advertising font, and included a 
"Children's Disney fun pack!" But that aside, train is still the classiest way to travel, and this train was no 
exception. Europe seems to offer countless ways to interact with your fellow man (or woman), preferably drink in hand. 
We chatted with our neighbor, a Spanish heavy metal enthusiast. At first when you begin studying a language, everyone 
seems impossibly distant and exotic. I know that I am getting capable when I can clearly see the Rocker within a Spaniard. 

("Rocker" must be international, allowing for the subtypes "American rocker" and "Spanish rocker". Incidentally "to rock" 
exists as an anglicism in Spanish: _"rockear."_ Example: "Prepare to rock!" = _"Que se preparen a rockear!"_)

Rocker: "Yeah, man! I was at a rock concert in Portugal---you know, death metal, Panthera, Alice in Chains! Rock, it 
was awesome!"
  
Me: "Cool, we're from the USA: we've got lots of rock there!"
  
Rocker: "Woah, you're from the United States?! How awesome! You guys have the best bands!! I would love to go and rock 
there! Rock on!"

It's great that so many of the people we met were genuinely excited and interested to meet us and to talk with us. That 
is the innocence or authenticity that I mentioned earlier.

The rocking of the train was annoying and I did not sleep well; plus the air conditioning was broken and the compartment 
was experiencing global warming. In the night I slipped on a shirt and walked to the bathroom in my skivvies. Everyone 
on the night trains goes about half-dressed at night. This intimate atmosphere makes me wonder how awful the terrorist 
attacks were on the Madrid commuter trains on [11 March 2004][1]. When everyone thinks of the public transport as an 
extension of their living room, it seems like a bombing would be even more traumatic. I paused on my way back to bed 
and stared out at the moonlit countryside slipping by.

## Madrid

Madrid again felt very large and cosmopolitan, and it was hard on us. After coffee, we took the metro into the center 
at the Puerta del Sol. What a mess: dirt and construction. We got an overpriced room in a dirty little hostel, bought 
some new clothes (my brother threw away his nastiest _camino-wear_), and went out to see the city.

I don't know why Madrid is not more known. It seems that in the US we always hear about Paris and Rome. Perhaps it has 
to do with the World Wars and the mass of American soldiers who passed through those cities. Madrid is extremely 
historic, with beautiful architecture---the buildings seem more liberated than we see in the US.

For example, imagine a large pure white granite building towering over you, crowned on top with a huge, black statue of 
a greek goddess. That is the [Metropolis Building][2].

![motropolis building](/assets//metropolis_building_04aug2008.jpg "Imagine a large pure white granite building towering over you.")
 
A certain [Palacio de Comunicaciones][4] is popularly known by the inhabitants of Madrid as the _Cathedral of 
Communications_ because it is so overly decorated.

![Palacio de Communicaciones](/assets//plaza_de_cibeles_palacio_de_communicaciones_madrid_2002.jpg "The 'Cathedral of Communications' is overly decorated.")
 
When we tired of riding on the tourist bus, we descended and drank beer on a side street. We were just off of the Gran 
Via, a high class shopping street, but in the space of a few yards, the ambiance turned quite lowbrow. Alarming women 
lounged outside of a "sexy shop." Two drunken guys leered and called out to pretty girls, who quickly went somewhere 
else. However, coexisting with this was a family playing Uno and other board games, groups of girlfriends gossipping, 
and other wholesome folks. We felt happy until we were charged 10 Euros for two beers ...

Madrid had beaten us. One afternoon was not enough time to even pierce the surface of this old, hardened, monied city. 
It had us figured out. Happy folks surrounded and ignored us. Stunning women cast us contemptuous looks. My old friend 
from Lausanne, Usue, who lives in Madrid, failed to meet us, something I had really looked forward to. We surrendered 
and went to bed early, lulled to sleep by the thumping of techo music late into the night.

The next day was the end. At 6am my alarm went off. It was a cheerless moment. I put off the inevitable for 5 more 
minutes, laying in bed thinking dark thoughts about my failures and shortcomings. Jason and I showered and packed up. 
Outside the streets still contained bands of revelers who had had a really good night. I thought we would have an hour 
or so for coffee, but passing by the metro stop, Jas revealed that his train left within an hour! The time had arrived! 
I gave him a hug, and we parted. I imagine I won't seem him again until Christmas.


## Flying Home

I was metal detected, X-rayed, had to take off my shoes, and turned upside down and shaken at least 452 times on my 
flight home. Does all of this really serve any purpose? Do the security folks ever find any evildoers? To pay back the 
US, which has been driving all of this nonsense, Europe now has special lines marked "Americans only." Sometimes it 
seems quite random. Passing through a certain line, an employee discovered that I had a lighter (!) and promptly 
confiscated it. He playfully flicked it on and off, then placed it in a bin along with hundreds of other lighters. The 
New York Times tells us these are sold at auction. It seems like an extra tax or fee you must pay in order to fly.

When I first started flying, it seemed that I was always placed next to beautiful girls. Back then I must have been 
protected by the patron saint of virgin flyers. Now I always end up next to ... for example on this trip:

1) an overweight businessman  
2) a mother with screaming infant  
3) a group of taiwanese Falun Gong missionaries (more later)

For one of my five flights, however, the saint really came through and between Madrid and Zurich I sat between 2 
beautiful girls.

What pleasure! My pulse races---of course I will have to speak with them, or else I will have missed a great 
opportunity. Two women present a special challenge. How to keep them both happy? 

One of the girls was a political science major from Sunnyvale (basically where I live) kind of random. She could not 
stop saying obvious things like: "Oh my god, Spain was so much fun!" and "If the flight is late we'll miss our 
connection to New York!" and my favorite "I hope the plane doesn't crash!"

The other girl was more interesting: a german au pair who studied Spanish instead of English. How cool! We had to speak 
in Spanish, which is automatically more fun. She was cute and laughed at my jokes. I liked her.

I flew across France, over the English channel, over the Irish sea and Ireland herself, Maine, Long Island, and finally 
into NYC. We are at a high peak of civilization to be able to pay 1 week's wages and tranquilly watch movies and eat 
dinner while sitting 40,000 feet in the air---and then to become cynical and bored with it! Ha---will this last? The 
gargantuan, super-complicated planes fill the airports---testifying to the power and wealth of their sponsor 
countries---Swissair, Air Madagascar, Pakistan International Airlines---burning fossil fuels, shaking the earth and the 
air. It never fails to awe me.

I got back to my apartment at about 11pm, for a healthy 24 hours total travel time. According to the internet the 
distance between Mountain View and Madrid is 5804 miles. That's an average speed of 241 miles an hour for 24 hours. If 
I was walking continuously at 4 miles an hour, it would have taken me 5804 miles / 4 miles an hour = 1451 hours / 24 
hours = 60 days of walking.

Here in Mountain View things seem to be much the same as I left them. Gatsby the cat is amazingly untraumatized by his 
two weeks of solitude. This morning I went to my coffee shop and it is still filled with geeks and nerds, although the 
pretty barrista is still there as well. Google has activated its free citywide wireless network, so I now have free 
internet in my apartment! I spoke with some friends, my parents ... Tomorrow it"s back to work: yay! Hopefully I will 
be able to conserve some of the energy and enthusiasm that travel always brings and apply it to my real life.

 [1]: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/11_March_2004_Madrid_attacks
 [2]: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolis_building
 [3]: http://blog.kevinmtrowbridge.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/07/metropolis_building_04aug2008.jpg
 [4]: http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palacio_de_Comunicaciones
 [5]: http://blog.kevinmtrowbridge.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/07/plaza_de_cibeles_-_palacio_de_communicaciones_madrid_2002.jpg
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["No More Walking!" and "the End of the World"]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2006-07-25-no-more-walking-and-the-end-of-the-world"/>
    <updated>2006-07-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/no-more-walking-and-the-end-of-the-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Since the last time I wrote, Jas and I have walked about 100km, arrived at Fisterra, and returned to Santiago (in bus, 
thank god).

Over eight days I walked 198km, or 123 miles. Jas, in 32 days, walked 800km, or 497 miles. This is no joke folks. You 
sleep in a room filled with 20 other pilgrims. Through the night, you hear their breathing, snores, and farts. Since the 
sun is very bright and hot in the afternoon, the pilgrims want to start walking as early as possible. So at an ungodly 
early hour the sleepers stir, zipping, unzipping, rustling, stuffing. Jas and I were often walking by 6:30am. It is dark 
in the early morning, so a small flashlight is used to pick out the yellow arrows that mark the trail. By 10am your feet 
hurt alot. Luckily bars and cafes are spaced out with some regularity along the route. At lunch I was still in pretty 
good shape; it is a heavenly time precisely because you were so miserable just before, the apparition of the cafe is like 
seeing the gates of heaven!

Arriving at Fisterra was the second 35km day for me. Thankfully there is no recording of my interior monologue ... but 
I can try to reproduce some of it here for your edification and amusement:

> &#8230; oww oww oww fucking hell shit damn oww oww &#8230;

In Spanish to a passerby: 

> &#8220;Excuse me, is there a bar coming up soon? No? Oh well, thanks and have a good day!&#8221;
> &#8230; stupid spanish people oww oww whoopee doo another old cross oww stupid trail &#8230;

Jas: 

> &#8220;Hey Kev, how are you doing?&#8221; 

Me, spoken: 

> &#8220;Great, what a beautiful day! Awesome! Cool!&#8221; 

After a while I sent Jas on ahead and continued at my own, slower pace. I forced myself to walk 2000 steps (about 1.5 km) 
between breaks. I counted the steps. When I reached 1999 steps, I literally threw myself on the ground and yanked off my 
shoes to massage my poor feet.

So the lesson of this is that:  

1) I am pretty flojo (get out Spanish dictionaries folks).  
2) Walking hundreds of miles is really hard and those who do finish entire long distance trails deserve respect!

When I arrived in Fisterra I searched with some desperation for the pilgrim alberge, only to meet Will, the fellow with 
one leg who walked the entire distance with crutches, smiling freshly at me.

&#8220;So, are you glad you´re done?&#8221; he asked in his chipper Aussie accent.

&#8212;&#8211;

Now that I am no longer in physical pain, the normal gliding of memories is taking place and causing me to wonder about 
walking the entire trail one day.

The Camino de Santiago follows the oldest places so that you notice, even beneath the ostentatious cruft of a large 
modern town, the familiar old medieval architecture that shows the town has existed for hundreds or thousands of years. 
Walking really does cause you to appreciate the uniqueness and the beauty of the places you are passing through; when 
we returned in bus it took two hours, we saw that we had actually walked a great distance, but from a bus, the little 
towns just looked boring and sleepy&#8212;we knew better, we knew about the nice old lady who rented us a room, we knew 
about the great restaurant that prepared us sandwiches, we knew about the shady lane with wind in the trees, the 
incredible first sighting of the ocean at the cresting of a hill!

&#8212;&#8211;

Fisterra is a beautiful little port town with truly awesome views up and down the coast. Jas and I stayed in a hostel 
with a balcony facing the ocean. It cost 30 euros for a night&#8212;pay at the bar and get the keys, you don´t even have to 
give your name! When I staggered into the room I threw open the windows to bright light shining in and the cawing of 
seagulls. I took a bath, the water turned a curious color.

We walked up to the lighthouse at the tip of the cabo to see the sunset. I drank a few beers with Jesus, a fellow who 
looks like Antonio Banderas but who is mysteriously German. We tried to make some sense of the Camino. What did this 
experience mean for our lives?

The sun flared out pinkly from behind clouds. Sailboats tacked north into the wind. Waves crashed far below and children 
scampered on the edge of the cliff.

I&#8221;m not sure &#8230; but I must have traveled to Europe and learned these languages for a reason. I should trust my 
instincts; this really is an amazing place which shows that progress is possible and that the US is off track in many 
areas &#8230; it&#8217;s not all in my head. I need to be braver and work harder to accomplish something with my life.

&#8212;&#8211;

Today we are back in Santiago. The feast of Santiago was two days ago, so the city no longer feels the anticipation of 
that event; life seems to be back to normal here &#8211; if this is the normal life of a 1000 year old pilgrimage 
destination jewel-like city.

Jason&#8217;s pilgrim friends have dispersed, so there are no more Euro perpetual parties. We somehow miraculously bumped 
into one of his teachers from Grenada and had dinner with her. Since she is not a pilgrim and feels, perhaps rightly, 
that it&#8217;s insane to walk hundreds of kilometers, we moved decisively out of the pilgrim ambiance and had a normal 
conversation&#8212;perhaps learning something about what life is really like for Spanish people in their 30s.

We read the Spanish papers at breakfast this morning and learned more about the ridiculous crap going on between Israel 
and Lebanon. Sigh &#8230; the real world reasserts itself. Tonight we take the night train to Madrid; tomorrow we will meet 
with Usue for dinner. On Sunday I fly home to California and to work.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Santiago De Compostela FAQ]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2006-07-22-santiago-de-compostela-faq"/>
    <updated>2006-07-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/santiago-de-compostela-faq</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[After walking 112km in 5 days, Jas and I have arrived in Santiago de Compostela.

Many of the pilgrims have come from much, much farther away than I have. Jas, for example, started in Roncesvalles, on 
the boarder with France, 800km, 30 days ago. If that seems impressive, a man named Will recently lost one of his legs in 
an accident---and walked the same distance with a set of crutches. A man in his eighties, blind, walked with his two 
grown children. One incredible girl started walking 3 months ago from her home in southern Germany.

Why are all of these people walking to Santiago de Compostela? Obviously it is one of the best known Christian 
pilgrimage destinations, just as Mecca is a destination for Muslims. One would expect the religious dimension of the 
trail to be stronger, but I have been pleasantly surprised &#8211; I have not yet met anyone who I would characterize 
as pushily religious. The pilgrim rates of drinking, smoking, flirting, and falling in love seem to be near European 
norms. The Camino seems to be a good example of a post-religious phenomenon: following tradition, doing something 
different, striving for an inner goal---these seem to be the goals the pilgrims search.

## FAQ for Santiago de Compostela

**Q: What is Santiago de Compostela?**

A: Santiago de Compostela is a city in northwestern Spain where legend holds that the body of Saint James, 3rd apostle 
to Jesus, is buried. The whole subject is treated in depth at the Wikipedia entry on [Saint James][1].

**Q: "Santiago" does not sound at all like "James"---where did this name come from?**  

A: Apparently in Latin James is Iacobus, over time Sant Iacobus became Santiago.

> St. James the Moorslayer, one of the most valiant saints and knights the world ever had … has been given by God to 
> Spain for its patron and protection.— Cervantes, 
[Don Quixote][2]  
  
This is heady stuff guys! We´re talking miracles, we´re talking legends, we´re talking about the Holy Grail!

&#8212;&#8211;

Even after my puny five days of walking, arriving at the city was quite impressive. As far as pilgrimage destinations 
go, I give it five stars. From the &#8220;Monte de Gozo&#8221; or &#8220;Peak of Joy&#8221; we first saw the city. In my dry, scholarly guide 
(which is awesome; we have started referring to it as &#8220;the book&#8221; with feigned trumpet fanfare) the authors permit 
themselves a little emotion for this moment:

> &#8220;The group of students with whom we trekked to Compostela in 1974, although largely secular in outlook, reacted &#8230; 
> as we spied the distant cathedral towers, most of us fell to our knees as tears welled up in our eyes.&#8221;

We needed to wade through a ring of ugly modern-ville (which my blistered feet did not appreciate) but soon enough we 
arrived at the old town. It is amazingly well preserved: narrow stone streets, stone buildings, stone fountains&#8212;and 
is quite large.

The final approach to the cathedral was through a tunnel. A busker played medieval music on bagpipes. We came into the 
square and saw the cathedral´s facade&#8212;a baroque monstrosity full of statues and appropriately covered with moss and 
looking very old. We sat in the square and stared at it, thinking about 1200 years of pilgrims doing the same.

After a time we began to meet other friends of my brother. On the ground in the center of the square the European 
council had laid a plaque speaking about the brotherhood of man and all that. It was quite cool.

Other activities of the past days:

* European perpetual party! We got swept into a crowd of French folks. I had to translate for the Europeans. Ha ha ha&#8212;I laugh.

* Catholic mass&#8212;anyone who is catholic must do this pilgrimage! It was very nice&#8212;they read off the names of the 
pilgrims who arrive each day&#8212;as we were saying, almost 500 per day in this time of the year, and Saint James&#8221; feast 
day is coming on the 25th. I am not catholic, but I cannot fail at times to be awed by the catholic church&#8212;its 
incredible age, its international nature, its wealth, financial and cultural, and the power it still retains.

* Reading from &#8220;the book&#8221; and trying to learn more about these buildings, sculptures, traditions, and life.

* Market day&#8212;thousands of little old ladies doing their shopping. It´s awesome to see the elderly people walking, 
living together in their wonderful city&#8212;it seems better than how it works in the US.

Now today we are leaving for &#8220;Finisterre&#8221;&#8212;the end of the western world for the Romans. It is 86 km further west and 
we are planning to arrive there in 3 days.

 [1]: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_James_the_Great
 [2]: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don_Quixote &#8220;Don Quixote&#8221;
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Llegado (Arrival) in Madrid]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2006-07-18-llegado-arrival-in-madrid"/>
    <updated>2006-07-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/llegado-arrival-in-madrid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[I have not been in Madrid for five years, my memories of the city are somewhat vague. This Sunday the weather was 
comfortably hot, the sun strong and bright. Is Madrid really that much farther south than San Francisco? As I stood in 
the customs line, my phone roamed to ´Telefonica Movistar,´ I cached my last dollars, and I felt the growing force of 
Spain:

*   The guard at the douana asked me questions in Spanish as he indolently flipped through my passport (funcionarios are 
government employees for life and cannot be fired).
*   I sat with an American family on the plane; an NYC mother with an infant &#8211; I could see the beginnings of shock 
as she contemplated taking care of her family in this new non-anglophone environment.
*   A 17 year old girl, pretty, from Alpharetta GA, had resourcefully arranged two weeks in a Spanish summer camp to work 
on her spanish---smart and capable, she would do well, but her nervousness was palpable as the change of language washed 
over her.

Everyone should experience, preferably alone, the shock of linguistic immersion in a foreign country---when I first did 
this, at 18, I was terrified! In retrospect I smile at my younger self, but at the time even walking down the street was 
a challenge---what if someone spoke to me and I was unable to answer? I bought bread in a store, it was so cheap, 
although it looked a little pale and unpalatable; later as I chewed on gummy inedible dough, I realized that 
_Pain demi-cuit_ means "half baked bread." Oops! 

I took the metro to Madrid's northward facing train station---the Madrid metro is huge! More than 10 lines cross in a 
tangled network that must rival neuronal connections in the brain. From the train station, the all electric train glided 
north on precisely engineered rails. Two friendly Spanish guys were returning north from vacations in Mayorca (I learned 
that there is another island named Menorca---very cute.). We had the first of many uncomfortable political conversations 
I must always endure when traveling in Europe---it seems ironic that I (europhile and spanish speaking) am expected to 
answer for the spastically autistic actions of the American government. The Spanish guys asked about my itinerary and 
suggested alternations, and when we got off of the train in Leon they walked with me to the ticket counter and spoke to 
the agent with me.

An east to west train took me from Leon to Sarria---we passed off of the 'mesata' and into the mountains of 
Galicia---beautiful, I had not realized how wonderful the landscape is: green soaring mountains with occasional spires 
of exposed rock, waterfalls tumbling into deep blue lakes. We stopped in a sleepy abandoned station for 20 minutes "to 
smoke cigarretes." The cars in the train had plush deep green seats and were stylized in a manner that must have dated 
the car from the era of Franco.

I was sitting next to a troop of Spanish boy scouts "Escoutes"---they laughed and word spread quickly that they had met 
an American boy scout from California. Many questions ensued: Are the people in California all as beautiful as the ones 
in the movies? Answer: Tragically no. Do American grocery stores really have bags made of brown paper---apparently in 
Spain they are only plastic.

Jas and I met at the Sarria train station like clockwork. We walked to the albergo where he had arranged rooms for the 
night. Here starts the real fun---but it is a big subject that I should treat properly.

Abbreviatedly:

We have been walking for two days now; about 20/30 kilometers per day. Apparently, arriving so far along the route, I 
have missed some of the most amazing historical sites, but there are still plenty of 12th century churches, ancient tiny 
villages, and beautiful countryside.

There are many other pilgrims, Jas and I (EE and Math majors) figure there are about 500 per day at this time of the 
year; next month is typically the highest, there might be about 30% more. These folks are very interesting---many 
French, German, and Scandinavian---relatively few Americans---a wide diversity of ages, from old (80 years!!) to very 
young children. We made friends with a family and they taught us a Spanish song about _"Tengo una vida pirata, con mi 
botella de ron!!"_ The adorable children were singing the song with gusto.

Last night in Portomarin after we got off of the trail (the only negative part so far is a lot of walking!! but I 
suspect it will have dividends) we sat in a bar and called out to my brother's many friends as they came off of the 
trail. This triggered a nice Euro perpetual party which moved from bar to bar to restaurant to finish with bottles of 
wine in a little park.

Boo! Good stuff! Jas and I rock at Spanish and we are charming everyone with silly jokes. A whole country for us to 
explore; it's like someone gave us a great big Christmas present! It seems amazing that you can step off of a plane and 
immediately interact so intimately with these dark, energetic people: curious eyes note your foreignness when you step 
in a bar, everyone is interested to hear the story of how two Americans came to be walking the "Camino de Santiago!"
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
