<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Outdoors | Kevin Trowbridge]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/blog/categories/outdoors/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-07T17:02:28-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kevin Trowbridge]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[kevinmtrowbridge@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Public Transportation Backpacking Trip to Point Reyes]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2009-07-09-public-transportation-backpacking-trip-point-reyes"/>
    <updated>2009-07-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/public-transportation-backpacking-trip-point-reyes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[I recently went on an extremely pleasant two-night backpacking trip. In itself that's not so remarkable. However, I did 
it without setting foot in a car—I accomplished all of the transportation to-and-fro using the public transportation 
system here in the San Francisco Bay Area.

It took a little digging to figure out how to do it. I think that people who enjoy backpacking tend to own cars, and 
people who take public transportation don't tend to be outdoorsy. But we are in San Francisco after all! There are 
surely other people like me, so I figure it's worth documenting for anyone else who is googling for backpacking trips.


## From San Francisco to Point Reyes using Public Transportation

There are three steps.

1. First take 'Golden Gate Transit' bus #70 north to San Rafael.

2. Then take the West Marin Stagecoach North Route #68 to Olema.

3. Then walk the final 3/4 of a mile to the Bear Valley Visitor Center.

![a map with arrows illustrating the steps](/assets//overview_map.png "An overview of the steps
to get from San Francisco to Point Reyes via Public Transit.")

You've arrived!  Get your backpacking permit, and head into the park.

Here are the specific times for one possible itinerary:

1. From Market & 7th in downtown SF, take the 'Golden Gate Transportation Service' bus #70 north to San Rafael.  You 
leave Market & 7th at 6:35am (pshew!) and arrive in San Rafael at 7:31am.  The reason we have to leave so early is that 
there are only four West Marin Stagecoach busses per day, and you need to get to San Rafael soon enough to take one of 
them.

![screenshot of a bus schedule](/assets//bus_70_ggt1.png "Schedule for Golden Gate Transit #70 from
San Francisco to San Rafael.")

[The full schedule for GGT bus 70.](http://goldengatetransit.org/schedules/pages/Route_702.html#wp1060821)

2. From San Rafael Transit center, take the West Marin Stagecoach west to Olema.

You can see the [West Marin Stagecoach page here](http://www.marintransit.org/stageschedules.html) and download the [PDF 
version of the schedule here](http://www.marintransit.org/pdf/northrouteschedule.pdf).

![screenshot of a bus schedule](/assets//west_marin_stagecoach_outbound.png "West Marin Stagecoach #68 schedule from San Rafael to Olema.")

2b (optional). Eat a hearty lunch in Olema to get strength for the upcoming hiking! ;)

3. Walk about a mile to the Point Reyes Bear Valley Visitor Center.  See a [google map of the walk here](http://maps.google.com/maps?f=d&source=s_d&saddr=olema&daddr=Bear+Valley+Visitor+Center+%4038.041104,-122.800294&hl=en&geocode=%3BFRB2RAIdWjeu-A&mra=ls&dirflg=w&sll=38.0423,-122.79374&sspn=0.013874,0.023346&ie=UTF8&z=16).


## In Point Reyes

It's not exactly relevant to the thesis of this article, but I can't resist gushing about how beautiful the park was---it 
definitely exceeded my expectations.

The first night I walked about 8 miles in to Wildcat camp ... located in a field above a remote beach.  Up above the 
camp there's a bluff with a bench that has simply stunning views along the coast in both directions.

![beautiful view of the California coast](/assets//dscf0161.jpg "Looking south towards double point from a bluff above Wildcat Camp.")

There was a lot of wildlife in the park—I kept stumbling across deer---like this handsome buck with showy, velveted 
antlers:

![a buck standing in a meadow at twilight](/assets//buck.jpg "A handsome buck with velveted antlers.")

Also, the campsites are quite nice.  It's not rough backpacking really—the camps all have nice pit toilets which are not 
at all smelly, potable water, and charcoal grills.  I didn't take advantage of the grills this time, but next time I 
will certainly pack in a frozen steak for the first evening's dinner.

![a beautiful sunset](/assets//dscf0217.jpg "A fantastic sunset from Mt. Wittenburg.")


## Returning

It's basically the opposite.  Again there are only 4 West Marin Stagecoaches per day so you have to schedule around 
them. 
 
I chose to exit the park around noon.  I ate lunch (again) in Olema (there's a nice restaurant there right at the 
intersection of Highway 1 and Francis Drake Blvd).  The bus came by at 1:45.  I was back in San Rafael at 3pm.  Then I 
took Golden Gate Transit #101 back into the city, arriving around 4pm.


### Other links

Note that to backpack in Point Reyes you need a permit and a reservation.  See the [Point Reyes website](http://www.nps.gov/pore/planyourvisit/publictransportation.htm)
for more information.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Public Transportation Backpacking Trip 2, Skyline-to-the-sea]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2009-07-09-public-transportation-backpacking-trip-2-skyline-to-the-sea"/>
    <updated>2009-07-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/public-transportation-backpacking-trip-2-skyline-to-the-sea</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[This past weekend I attempted another 'public transportation backpacking trip.'  This time however I brought along my 
girlfriend---which ended up making things more adventurous, and well, yes, more fun, although, I had to modify my 
exquisitely prepared plan.


## What is the Skyline-to-the-Sea trail?

First things first.  [Skyline-to-the-Sea][2] is a 30 mile hike from Castle Rock State Park (which is up on the topmost 
ridge of the Santa Cruz Mountains) down to the Pacific Ocean, passing through [Big Basin State Park][3] on the way.  Big 
Basin is a pretty fantastic spot, the first California State Park, and with a [great history][4] based around the 
preservation of the awesome old redwood trees that are there ...

![Skyline-to-the-Sea trail in the context of the larger Bay Area.][5]

It's the 'crown-jewel' of hikes in the Bay Area (as I have heard it called) ... and so I had to do it, since I have been 
having a backpacking renaissance lately.


## How to do it with Public Transportation

Well---first of all, it makes good sense to do it that way, because it's a through hike, that is, not a loop, so in 
order to do it with a car, you would either need two cars, or someone to pick you up when you've finished.

At the Pacific Ocean end, you can get the Santa Cruz bus system to pick you up at Waddell Creek and take you to Santa 
Cruz.

However, you can't get to Castle Rock State Park with a bus.  My solution was to get to Saratoga with buses and then 
take a taxi the rest of the way ... the taxi cost $30.

The following two sections detail the steps.


### Outward Bound

<table class="table">
  <caption>A list of numbered steps describing how to get from San Francisco to Castle Rock State Park. The numbers correspond to the numbers on the map below.</caption>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Step</th>
      <th>From</th>
      <th>To</th>
      <th>Using</th>
      <th>Cost</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>San Francisco</td>
      <td>Santa Clara</td>
      <td><a href="http://www.caltrain.com/timetable.html">Caltrain</a></td>
      <td>$7.75</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>Santa Clara</td>
      <td>Saratoga</td>
      <td><a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=d&amp;source=s_d&amp;saddr=Santa+Clara+Caltrain+station,+Santa+Clara,+CA+95050&amp;daddr=Saratoga,+CA&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=FdP1OQIdCGa7-A%3B&amp;mra=ls&amp;dirflg=r&amp;date=07%2F08%2F09&amp;time=1:38pm&amp;ttype=dep&amp;noexp=0&amp;noal=0&amp;sort=&amp;tline=&amp;sll=37.30505,-121.97373&amp;sspn=0.107459,0.174751&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;ll=37.308468,-121.979313&amp;spn=0.107454,0.174751&amp;z=13&amp;start=0">Santa Clara Bus System</a></td>
      <td>$3.50 (2 rides at $1.75 apiece—no transfers)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>Saratoga</td>
      <td>Castle Rock State Park</td>
      <td><a href="http://www.yellowcheckercab.com">Taxi</a></td>
      <td>$30 … plus we gave the driver a $5 tip for $35 total.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

![Outward bound Public Transportation from SF to Castle Rock State Park.][7]


### Returning

<table class="table">
  <caption>
    A list of numbered steps describing how to get from Waddell Beach (on Highway 1 at the end of the trail) to San 
    Francisco. The numbers correspond to the numbers on the map below.</caption>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Step</th>
      <th>From</th>
      <th>To</th>
      <th>Using</th>
      <th>Cost</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>Waddell Beach</td>
      <td>Santa Cruz</td>
      <td><a href="http://www.scmtd.com/schedule/sched40wd.html">Santa Cruz Transportation</a></td>
      <td>$1.50</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>Santa Cruz</td>
      <td>San Jose</td>
      <td><a href="http://www.scmtd.com/routes/rt17.html">Santa Clara Bus System</a></td>
      <td>$4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>San Jose</td>
      <td>San Francisco</td>
      <td><a href="http://www.caltrain.com/timetable.html">Caltrain</a></td>
      <td>$7.75</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

Here&#8217;s a [google transit page][8] showing the route from Santa Cruz to San Francisco. (Google doesn&#8217;t seem to know about 
route 40 (step 1 in the table above)—which goes along the coast.)

![Return public transportation from Wadell Beach to San Francisco.][9]

Return public transportation from Wadell Beach to San Francisco.


## Permits & Reservations

You need permits to stay in the Skyline-to-the-Sea backcountry campgrounds. In my experience they weren&#8217;t hard to get 
&#8230; we did it on the fourth of July weekend and had no problem getting the reservations.

This seems to be the official page with the information (the Skyline-to-the-Sea has a sort of scattered internet 
presence, I find): 

The [PDF file][10] they list there is especially useful with the telephone number to call to make the reservations, 
information on fees, and a table of mileages between camps.

831-338-8861 is the number of the Big Basin State Park HQ, and they are also the office which takes care of reservations
for Skyline-to-the-Sea.

My experience was basically this:

I called the number and reserved one night in the Waterman Gap Trail Camp, and one night in the Twin Redwoods Trail 
Camp.  I mailed them a check for $5 to secure the reservation (a _reservation fee_).  They mailed me a little blue 
postcard which acted as proof that I had paid.  When we started the hike, at Castle Rock State Park, I showed the 
postcard to the ranger there, and paid her another $20 which was the actual _campground fee_.  A little confusing, 
but hey, it works.

You can buy some [awesome maps of the area][11] for $13 from the Sempervirens Fund &#8230; I would suggest getting these.
You can order them online, or we also saw them in the information center at Big Basin State Park.


## Our Experience

We left San Francisco at 8:15am on July 4th using Caltrain. The bus dropped us off at the &#8216;West Valley College&#8217;&#8212;this 
is about 1.7 miles from the Saratoga downtown &#8230; so we were worried for a little while that there was no such thing as 
a Saratoga downtown &#8230; however, there is, it just took a little walking to get there&#8212;here&#8217;s the route we took:

![There&#8217;s a 1.7 mile walk from where the bus drops you off to downtown Saratoga.][12]

We got there around 11am and ate a really nice lunch in an Italian Restaurant &#8216;Ristorante Da Mario&#8217; &#8230; to fortify 
ourselves for the trek ahead we had to drink at least two good Birra Moretti!

![Italian food fortifies us for the trek!][13]

Then we called the taxi (San Jose Yellow Cab: 650-321-1234) &#8230; the driver showed up and took us up to Castle Rock State 
Park&#8212;a beautiful drive.  It cost about $35 dollars including tip.

![The intrepid hikers take to the trail!][14]

At Castle Rock State Park we showed the ranger lady the reservation card we had (see above) and paid her $20 cash to pay 
for the campsites.  (It costs the same no matter how many nights you camp, pretty cool, huh?)

![Thirty-one miles to Waddell Beach!][15]

The first afternoon we had about 10 miles to hike.  The first portion of the trail goes through Chaparral &#8230; it&#8217;s 
fairly exposed to the sun and also fairly rocky, with steep drop-offs.  So we were fairly hot and the hiking required 
attention.

![Beautiful views are to be had in the upper portions of the hike.  This is from the Saratoga Gap Trail &#8230; between the Castle Rock parking lot and the Castle Rock Trail Camp.][16]

About 1/3 of the way to Waterman Gap (only about 2 miles from the Castle Rock Parking Lot) is the Castle Rock Trail 
Camp &#8230; if you arrive very late, you could stay here—they have water available, a pit toilet, and&#8212;what&#8217;s awesome for 
a devoted fire worshiper like myself—they actually allow campfires and even sell firewood there in the camp.  (Self 
service, but only during the &#8216;winter&#8217; / &#8216;not fire season&#8217;.)

![The Castle Rock Trail Camp &#8230; it has a telephone, running water, picnic tables, allows campfires, and even sells firewood \(during the non-fire season\) for $7 per bundle.  The site is not very scenic though.][17]

The trail was a little confusing from that point on.  We took a wrong turn and ended up going to &#8216;Frog Flat 
Campground&#8217;&#8212;and had to backtrack.  That added about 4/5th of a mile to our hike.  I had quite stupidly forgotten to 
bring the maps that I had ordered online (see above)!  It was just about the worst thing to forget as &#8230; without a map, 
you feel like you are a bit blind, and you can easily get confused.

![The trail claims to be easy to follow but in my experience, there is a mishmash of trails &#8230; be sure to obtain the proper maps before you leave, otherwise you may end up walking further than you need to \(as well did!\) &#8230;][18]

Meg was pretty tired that night when we finally arrived at Waterman Gap.  To all boyfriends who want to take their 
girlfriend hiking&#8212;don&#8217;t be ambitious guys, be sure to start small.  ;)

The next day we kept hiking from Waterman Gap down to the Big Basin State Park HQ—another 10 mile hike.  The trail was a 
little easier, with more relatively flat and spongy trail through pine forests and less rocky and exposed trail along 
chaparral.  In a few places the trail did emerge and we had more beautiful views towards the ocean:

![Another beautiful view, this one from just above Big Basin State Park, on the straight-up Skyline-to-the-Sea trail just before the descent to Opal Creek.][19]

![Your humble narrator, Kevin Trowbridge.][20]

Unfortunately, by the time we got to Big Basin HQ, we were exhausted.  Meg especially did not have the right shoes for 
the expedition and her feet were very painful.  It&#8217;s one thing to be ambitious for yourself, but I made the mistake of 
expecting Meg to make the same sacrifices as myself.

We stayed in one of the &#8216;hike in&#8217; campsites at Big Basin HQ &#8230; they have nice facilities and allow you to have 
campfires.  Unfortunately the campsite is two miles from the Big Basin HQ!  We were very discouraged at this news 
(2 more miles of walking!!)&#8212;and Meg and I plopped down on a bench in front of the HQ and started sniffling and looking 
miserable.  Graciously, the rangers took pity on us and offered us a ride to our campsite in their truck!  We were 
touched, and felt much better.  Thank you to the Big Basin HQ ranger staff.  ;)

The next day I couldn&#8217;t bring myself to put Meg through more pain so we discussed together and decided to try to 
hitchhike to Santa Cruz.  We obtained some cardboard and sharpies from the camp store and made this awesome sign:

![Oh, the immortal shame!  We had to abandon the trek at Big Basin State Park and hitchhike to Santa Cruz!][21]

After about two hours of sticking our thumbs out, one of the employees drove us down to Boulder Creek:

![Luckily one of the young folks who work at the Big Basin State Park Grocery Store drove us to Boulder Creek on his lunch break.][22]

From Boulder Creek we were able to head down to Santa Cruz using buses.  We checked into a hotel (with an awesome hot 
tub!) and cleaned ourselves up.  Then we went for a walk on the boardwalk and watched the moon rise&#8212;and we were happy. 

So everything ended up fine.  And it&#8217;s fun to have an adventure!


[2]: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skyline-to-the-Sea_Trail
[3]: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Basin_Redwoods_State_Park
[4]: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sempervirens_Club

[10]: http://bigbasin.org/NewFiles/Skyline_to_the_Sea_Trail_Camp_Information.pdf
[11]: http://www.sempervirens.org/store.htm

[6]: http://maps.google.com/maps?f=d&source=s_d&saddr=Santa+Clara+Caltrain+station,+Santa+Clara,+CA+95050&daddr=Saratoga,+CA&hl=en&geocode=FdP1OQIdCGa7-A%3B&mra=ls&dirflg=r&date=07%2F08%2F09&time=1:38pm&ttype=dep&noexp=0&noal=0&sort=&tline=&sll=37.30505,-121.97373&sspn=0.107459,0.174751&ie=UTF8&ll=37.308468,-121.979313&spn=0.107454,0.174751&z=13&start=0
[8]: http://maps.google.com/maps?f=d&source=s_d&saddr=santa+cruz,+ca&daddr=San+Francisco,+CA&hl=en&geocode=&mra=ls&dirflg=r&date=07%2F08%2F09&time=1:38pm&ttype=dep&noexp=0&noal=0&sort=&tline=&sll=37.308468,-121.979313&sspn=0.107454,0.174751&ie=UTF8&ll=37.38778,-122.184757&spn=0.85872,1.39801&z=10&start=0

[5]: /assets//skyline_to_the_sea.png
[7]: /assets//outward_skyline_to_the_sea_public_transportation.png
[9]: /assets//return_skyline_to_the_sea_public_transportation.png
[12]: /assets//saratoga_walk.png
[13]: /assets//italian_food.jpg
[14]: /assets//intrepid_hikers.jpg
[15]: /assets//overview.jpg
[16]: /assets//view_1.jpg
[17]: /assets//castle_rock_trail_camp.jpg
[18]: /assets//signage.jpg
[19]: /assets//view_2.jpg
[20]: /assets//kevin_m_trowbridge.jpg
[21]: /assets//shame.jpg
[22]: /assets//good_samaritan.jpg]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
