<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Autobiographical | Kevin Trowbridge]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/blog/categories/autobiographical/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-31T10:38:18-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kevin Trowbridge]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[kevinmtrowbridge@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts on Weddings]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2015-03-22-thoughts-on-weddings"/>
    <updated>2015-03-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/thoughts-on-weddings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[NOTE: Meg and I were married on November 16th, 2013.  That's about 1.5 years ago at this point.  We got engaged during a 
trip to Costa Rica in November 2012.  Our wedding was a fascinating and completely consuming process and, occasioned 
many "deep thoughts."  I have attempted to capture some of them here.


# Basic attitude: what's actually happening here?

A wedding is a transaction between a community and a couple.  The couple is legitimized, and promised aid in their
future growth, and the couple, in turn, swears a most excellent oath that they truly do love, and will love one another,
and help one another to grow in the best possible way.

Much of the advice given to couples emphasizes an egoistic point of view: "it's my / our special day."  But, really it 
is a "community building" event.  You're telling a story to your community about itself and your role within it.  Focus
on your mate and your wedding guests: with such potent and wonderful raw ingredients as a wedding is made of, you
literally cannot fail.


## The importance of focusing&mdash;and punting on the other things
   
Too many people try to "do it all" ... a wedding planner friend told me stories of $1000 bags of rose petals and such ... 
pick just a few "special things" and focus your efforts on those.  Punt or make the minimum necessary effort on the 
others.  You only need a few truly memorable things to make your wedding a great success.
   
We focused on:

* choosing a most excellent venue: it was at a summer camp, and once they arrived, no one had to drive anywhere
* performances of music and theater: a live band, the Talent Show
* the photo boards (this was Kevin's big project)

We punted on:

* the food (we gave slight guidance and then delegated to the chef completely)
* the music (outside of the live band, we had a Spotify playlist)
* the place cards (we just bought a set of cardboard numbers for $15 and printed an Excel spreadsheet of seat assignments)


## If things go wrong

You're not doing it all yourself.  People bring their best selves to a wedding--if  anything goes wrong, you will have
help.  I remember, when we wanted to go to "The Boogie Barn," we hadn't  figured out how to carry over the keg from the
dining hall.  In the actuality, there was a team of 5 burly guys who  carried it wherever we went.  When loading or
unloading things, we had more helpers than we  knew what to do with.

After all, as Cole Porter said: it's "Nice work if you can get it."  So relax, and savor  this once in a lifetime
experience.  You will never again have the people you love most in the world collected together,  for this reason.  As
in any creative act, be in awe of your ingredients, and put them together simply, with   good timing. 

The reality of the love that underlies human community will pierce through your humble situation and it won't be just 
any wedding, it will be the wedding, the one archetypal wedding, you will play the archetypal roles ... the  fierceness,
the brightness, the tenderness, the hope for the future, the reality of the pain and loss in the past, the mystery of "what's is all about?" ...  it will all
create a beautiful, mystical feeling ... and, the psychological transformation to your new life stage, will be
accomplished.


# Practicalities


## Choosing a venue (more space and time is better)

Each hour is precious.  Your goal is to enable more "quality  time" and reduce time spend figuring out banal logistics. 
The guests will not self-organize very much just out of  shyness, uncertainty, inertia, and other things to do.  

When we have traveled for weddings, say to New York City, with my unusually well organized college friends ...  I was
impressed by how much time we *did not* spend together.  The friends stayed in different areas of the city, or even  in
the same area, but separated by 10-20 blocks ... it looks small on a map but, in the morning when you consider:  "Where
to get coffee?" 20 blocks is barrier that blocks coordinated activity.  Also, the huge city has a pull of its  own, away
from the focus of your wedding.

These are a few of the reasons why we preferred a rural location for our wedding: we rented a summer camp.  Once the 
guests arrived on Friday night, they could park their cars, and not drive again until Sunday afternoon.  Most everyone 
slept onsite, and all meals were served onsite.  We were so happy with this decision.  It was a 
fundamental choice which made everything easier, cheaper, and created space and time to allow wedding energy to be 
focused.

Of course the summer camp idea isn't for everyone.  I think some of the ideas could be adapted to any wedding: getting
the cooperation of  a bar or restaurant to be the "community bar" for the weekend, for example, would give folks a
single  geographic location to focus on.  Consider the problem of what to do the night before the wedding: often the
wedding party will do their "rehearsal dinner" and leave everyone else in dark. If simple plans were laid just: "Billy's
Pizzaria is the official restaurant for the wedding and everyone should meet up there on Friday night" then, the wedding
party can join the other party as soon as they are done with their rehearsal, and you've created a fantastic night,
because, the anticipation of the two groups joining will create a good emotional arc.


## Roles for community members

Assign roles to your community members.  This makes the event feel organic and creates a feeling of participation,
ownership and pride in your group.  You most definitely want this.  If you have more community members than you have
roles, create more roles: for example, the girls in our friend group have the tradition of crafting decorations for the
reception.  On the Friday before the wedding we created a "Talent Show" ... but in a big way.  We asked anyone who
wanted to, to perform, and 7 groups agreed ... there was a Trapeze Act, an Improv Comedy show, my parents, aunts and
uncles sang  traditional church music, one friend wrote the most amazing "Gangsta Rap" with biographical lyrics ... I
created a playful "program" ... Another friend mixed the drinks for us.  Another friend carried the train of Meg's
wedding dress.  We asked our best old friend to be the officiant and she wrote an incredible speech for us.

This is why the traditional wedding has roles for the community: the wedding party, the Best Man's speech, the Maid of
Honor's speech ...


## Good news&mdash;spending more can make the feeling worse

> &#8220;After all, what really matters on your wedding day, what you’ll remember ‘til you’re old and gray, is not so much how 
it looked as how it felt.&#8221;
&#8211;&#8220;A Practical Wedding&#8221; Meg Keene

Meg and I both loved this quote and it summed up my experience of attending weddings.  The audience is supremely
intelligent and  cannot be fooled by mere expense and opulence.  In fact this can be off-putting as a sign of &#8220;something
to prove&#8221; and,  the distastefulness of waste.  And so, my favorite wedding of all time was done quite inexpensively, but
with great  attention, inventiveness, and love.  In general, what I&#8217;m trying to say is that relationship between price
and quality,  in weddings, is very slim.


## &#8220;Who are all these people?&#8221;: Photoboards

A wedding is a community building event.  Since this couple is going to stay together and may raise a baby, they are
going to need for their friends to coalesce around them.  There&#8217;s a good chance that, in large, before the wedding, most
of the people you invite,  will have no idea who the others are.  

The time flies by, and attendees will be lucky to gain a basic understanding of your family. The traditional structure
recognizes this and features your families and the wedding party, on purpose: so that the audience will take note of 
them and realize they are important in your life.

But if you realize the &#8220;educational nature&#8221; of a wedding &#8230; you can come up with other means of explaining just who 
everyone is.

My  way of doing this was to create a series of photoboards.  I organized them thematically: &#8220;Our Folks&#8221;, &#8220;Childhood&#8221;, 
&#8220;College / Travels&#8221;, &#8220;We Left our Hearts in San Francisco&#8221;, and &#8220;Meg & Kevin&#8221;.  

After a number of false starts, I  figured out the cheapest way:  I bought five &#8220;foam core&#8221; boards (XXX dimensions).  I
sorterd & selected the the pictures digitally (which was a huge job, looking through thousands of photos &#8230;).  I was
able to print these out on a color printer at  our local print shop (I think it cost something like $0.49 per page). 
Then, I cut them out of the 8.5x11&#8221; sheets using the paper cutter at the  print shop.  Finally I pinned the photos to the
foam core using thumbtacks.  

It was still a huge job!  But, this was the  speed / price compromise that I needed to make and, they were,
aesthetically in some ways, better than what I had originally planned.

And the photo boards were a huge success!  On the first evening, after the talent show, we saw some of our friends in the
dark dining hall (the lights were off), using their phones as flashlights to look through the photos.  Pictures are 
inherently fascinating to people.  Even babies and toddlers understand pictures.

These pictures helped the wedding attendees understand who they all were, in relation to themselves (if that  makes
sense).  It helped to contextualize our lives, our families, our past, and the great value and meaning of this event
for us.

XXX pictures of photo boards



## Digital vs traditional invitations &#8211; and timing of digital invitations

Weddings are an occasion when tradition takes over, and stipulates certain behaviors.  So, they evolves more slowly than
 normal life.  This is especially evident when you consider how the invitations and communications happen.  

In modern  life, most people organize themselves digitally.  We send text messages or emails or Facebook messages to
choose a time & place, and then we send reminders very soon beforehand.  You never need, anymore, to bring any physical
documents with you in order to locate where you&#8217;re supposed to be, because you can always just look it up on your phone,
or send a text message to confirm.

Weddings break this, because people send paper invitations, and often skip electronic communications.  I think this is
actually risky and a bad way to follow tradition.  

A quick story:

A few years ago, we were invited to Pim & Shane&#8217;s wedding in Southern California.  Pim had verbally told Meg that
the wedding was &#8220;at her neighbor&#8217;s house.&#8221;  We flew to Southern California.  We spent a night near Laguna Beach, we had
a romantic dinner, we were enjoying ourselves.  On Saturday we realized, that we had forgotten the paper wedding
invitation at home.  But, no big deal because, Pim had told Meg that the wedding was at &#8220;her neighbor&#8217;s house&#8221; and we
knew where Pim&#8217;s house was.  (Everyone we knew well was in the wedding party, and we didn&#8217;t want to bother them.)  So,
we found a hotel near to Pim&#8217;s house, and giving ourselves plenty of time, we showered, changed, and took a taxi to
Pim&#8217;s house, expecting the neighborhood to be crowded with tons of people.

Instead, we found the house absolutely deserted!  There wasn&#8217;t a person in sight and, no obvious &#8220;neighbor&#8217;s house&#8221;
where a wedding was taking place.  We finally got the bride&#8217;s brother on the phone, Tandy.

&#8220;Where&#8217;s the wedding at?  We&#8217;re at your house.  Is your neighbor&#8217;s house around the corner?&#8221;  We asked.  &#8220;You&#8217;re at my
house?  Which house?  Our parents&#8217; house?&#8221;  he asked, incredulously.  &#8220;Really?  The wedding is 30 miles from there!&#8221;

With our San Francisco brains, we had imagined &#8220;neighbor&#8217;s house&#8221; to be right down the street.  When, in reality, down
in SoCal, a &#8220;neighbor&#8217;s house&#8221; could be 30 miles away.

We jumped back into the taxi.  We rushed back to the hotel.  We got our car and drove frantically.  We took a wrong
turn, and had to turn around in the middle of the freeway.  We just barely made it.  The bride was walking down the
aisle when we arrived.

For me the moral of the story is that (besides for the obvious one that we were stupid to forget the invitation in San
Francisco) for such an important event as a wedding, it&#8217;s strange to totally change the way we communicate.

When Meg and I were married, we created a beautiful &#8220;Save the Date&#8221; card and mailed it out, months in advance, so that
people had something to hang on their refrigerators.  But, then we switched to digital communications.  We collected
everyone&#8217;s email addresses and created beautiful, informative emails which we sent several times as the wedding neared.

And most importantly, 2 days before the wedding, I sent one final email to everyone that contained the address of our
wedding venue, so that, as people were traveling, they would have all the information they needed at hand, on their
phones.


## Videography: the uncharted territory of wedding photography

We paid $2500 for a nice wedding photographer.  Professional wedding photographers are very good at one thing: lining
everyone up and taking traditional wedding pictures.  I think an amateur photographer might not have the crowd control
abilities to carve out the space for pictures.  And, those slightly staged pictures are invaluable.  They are some of
the best, highest quality pictures taken of folks in the prime of their lives.  Just look at your grandparents&#8217; wedding
pictures, if you are lucky enough to have them.  They&#8217;re treasures.

But, a few things:

Our friend Ian, who is a great photographer, took about 600 pictures.  Since Ian knows, and is known by, our group of
friends, he was able to evoke very authentic, characteristic expressions and situations.  In many ways, I much prefer
Ian&#8217;s photos (which were free) to the $2500 professional photographers photos.  

Another thing is, we punted on the idea of a videographer.  

Professional photographers don&#8217;t tend to take video, I think it&#8217;s either a different skill, hard to sell, or people
don&#8217;t realize they want this.  

However, if a picture is worth 1,000 words, a video must surely be worth a million.  You
most definitely want a video of your wedding ceremony, and of the special events during the reception.  When I look at
our wedding photos, I smile and they&#8217;re cute.  When I watch the video of our ceremony, and of the special events during
the reception.  When I look at our wedding photos, I smile and they&#8217;re cute.  When I watch the video of our ceremony, I am 
transported back to that moment.  It is invaluable to me.  

So, I think that wedding photographers should offer videography. In the absence of this, ask one of your mindful friends
to take a video with their iPhone.  Even a shitty video is infinitely better than none at all.  If you&#8217;re at weddings,
look around and if no one else is recording the ceremony, pull out your iPhone and grab a recording of it.  The bride
and groom will be so thankful to you later.

XXX link to Youtube channel


## The logistical spreadsheet
 
TODO


# Philosophy

Jung&#8217;s thoughts on ceremonies marking transitions through life&#8217;s phases


## The wedding, like a mass, is a very evolved ceremony and you should treat the various parts with respect.

For example, I have never been a big fan of the garter & bouquet toss.  They feel old-fashioned and, putting pressure on
the &#8220;unmarried people&#8221; is something I kinda resented, when I was unmarried.  However, this ceremony plays a role.  It
helps to transition the party from sit down dinner time, to dancing time.  The young people stand up and put on a show
for the older people &#8230; the young people will continue from here to dancing, and the older folks can observe, laugh,
and start conversations at the tables.  If you cut out this piece of the ceremony, you will have to invent your own
method to transition from dinnertime to dancing time.


## More thoughts on what weddings are and mean 
 
> &#8220;Today, Andy & Laurel got married, but really, I feel as if we all just did.&#8221;   &mdash;Meg Kliman 

Traditionally, there&#8217;s a good chance the union will produce children.  From the community&#8217;s perspective, it&#8217;s going to
have to care for these children.  As much as conservative people may think they&#8217;re doing it all on their own, in
reality, it really does &#8220;take a village&#8221; to raise a child.  In the extreme case,  imagine if the parents were to die. 
The care for the children would fall by default on the community.  

Traditionally, the community should discourage unmarried people from sleeping together, because if they were to have a
child, it would be born into an unstable situation and the likelihood that the community would have to assume its care
is higher.

For more modern people, a wedding represents a small concretization of the community&#8217;s social structure.  Even taking 
the thought of children out, the mental leap, the transition into a new life phase, the desire of the couple to make a
commitment to one another &#8230; is the source of the value of the ritual.

So, now we can see the transaction that is taking place.  The community says: we will recognize and legitimize your
relationship, however, you basically have to prove to us that you&#8217;re truly serious and, you have to swear your most
excellent oath to that effect.


### &#8220;Prove to us you&#8217;re truly serious&#8221; 

I think creating a wedding is a great way of doing this.  You are running a gauntlet. It is a most complicated and
involved test.  It takes sustained effort, patience, money and so forth.  

Additionally, it has a huge element of play and should in fact be, a lot of fun &#8216;cause, after all you are planning a 
party.

On our wedding day, after I finished running back and forth to the ceremony meadow, arguing with the sound people about
which music they should play, after I gave my groomsmen each their own individually created carefully picked out gifts
.. after I finalized my vows &#8230; after I saw the community girls working merrily on their decorating projects &#8230; after
I explained to my restauranteur friend who we carefully chose to mix the reception cocktails &#8230; after I discussed with
the maid of honor&#8217;s boyfriend, who we had asked to be our unofficial videographer &#8230; as I lined everyone up &#8230; as I
took Meg&#8217;s hand and stared out at the audience &#8230; I was exhausted and, I simply could not wait to be married.  

I eagerly desired with every fibre of my being that this transaction would be successfully completed.  The process had
literally wrung this feeling out of me.  And I think this is what Jung and Campbell are talking about when they discuss
ceremonies that shepard people through their life stages &#8230; what you&#8217;re looking for is a psychological transformation
to take place &#8230; and for your unconscious self to recognize that you are now married.


### The ceremony

The ceremony is much maligned &#8230; but really it is the moment, by far, that has the most potential.  It can be
heartbreakingly beautiful and meaningful.

It should be emotional!  It should give people an opportunity to cry.  To contemplate the slow human
drama.  It&#8217;s much maligned as boring, incomprehensible, long &#8230; to this I say: You&#8217;re in charge.  20-30 minutes is a
good length.  The ceremony can be too short or uneventful.  In this case, people will feel disappointed &#8230; they will
feel as if nothing much happened.


### While the groom is waiting for the bride

The unspoken fear at this moment is that the bride (or groom) may not show up. It&#8217;s ok to go slowly at this moment &#8230;
if you let the audience get a little nervous, they will feel a bigger catharsis at its resolution.  Additionally I think 
playing beautiful and lonely music can heighten the feeling of emptiness and longing.


### The joy that the audience feels when the officiant declares: &#8220;I present to you, for the very first time: Meg & Kevin
Trowbridge!&#8221;
 
TODO &#8230; this is the joy of new life


### A ritual that helps you to transition into a new stage of life

The bride and groom are playing archetypal roles.  The bride is &#8220;everywoman&#8221; and the groom &#8220;everyman.&#8221;  When people
watch your wedding, they are either anticipating, or reliving, their own.  

Additionally, it marks one of the major transitions in life, from childhood, to maturity, and so it&#8217;s a &#8220;once in a
lifetime&#8221; moment.  Life stretches from this moment, towards death.  There&#8217;s a good chance the couple will procreate and
have a baby.  

All this inevitably pushes the mind towards meaningful thoughts of life and death.  This is well and good and the source
of the great power of weddings.

People get so egocentric about weddings.  It is good to label these tendencies as &#8220;groomzillo&#8221; and &#8220;bridezilla.&#8221;  On one
level yes, it is a celebration of your relationship and your lives to this point &#8230; but (see elsewhere in this essay)
it is also a universal human ceremony that is meaningful to everyone involved.  It&#8217;s not really all about you, it&#8217;s
about your evolving role in your community.

So the right philosophy is to express your love and respect for you wife and your guests by serving them in the creation
of a comfortable, respectful, beautiful celebration.  Perhaps the biggest and most meaningful party you will ever
create.  Do not focus on yourself and &#8220;your special day.&#8221;  Put the focus on your mate and on your guests.


### Wedding is an  emotional arc

A truly great album will have a shape to it: start with a bang to earn &#8220;suspension of disbelief&#8221; &#8230; don&#8217;t blow your
best material, save it for the end.  Will you have multiple peaks and mellow periods, or will you have simpler shape?

If you have good control over your material, you can meld a satisfying arc.

> “Most of our best numbers were in what I call the tempo of the heartbeat. That’s the tempo that strikes people easiest
because, without their knowing it, they are moving to that pace all their waking hours. Music to me is sex—it’s all tied
up somehow, and the rhythm of sex is the heartbeat. I usually try to avoid scoring a song with a climax at the end.
Better to build about two-thirds of the way through, and then fade to a surprise ending. More subtle. I don’t really
like to finish by blowing and beating in top gear.”

Granata, Charles L. (2003-10-01). Sessions with Sinatra: Frank Sinatra and the Art of Recording (p. 94). Chicago Review
Press. Kindle Edition. 



# Appendix


## Grooms&#8217; broken &#8220;cultural script&#8221;

I read many books, my favorite of which was [A Practical
Wedding](http://www.amazon.com/Practical-Wedding-Affordable-Meaningful-Celebration/dp/0738215155) &#8230; and did a lot of
research online.  I was quite impressed with our society&#8217;s cultural script for grooms.  Grooms are supposed to be:
man-children who think the whole wedding is crazy and nonsense &#8220;women are crazy&#8221; so just put up with them and say yes to
whatever they demand the bachelor party is the the most important part of the wedding and, at the bachelor party you
just HAVE to have sex with a stripper, do cocaine, and get into fights .. it&#8217;s not hard to find the most demeaning
obnoxious advice imaginable, directed at grooms.

I was very interested in the wedding.  I paid for about half of it.  I read a [New York Times article titled &#8220;Burden of
Paying for Wedding Bells Shifts](http://www.nytimes.com/2010/04/04/fashion/weddings/04FIELD.html)  which mentioned 

http://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2014/07/24/what-wedding-traditions-should-be-tossed/its-the-grooms-day-too

Imagine, instead of a wedding, you were planning a huge, no-expenses party for the most important people in your life. 
What is more, you get to introduce different groups of people (your college friends, your wife&#8217;s friends, your old
roommates in the city, your family, your wife&#8217;s family) to one another.  It&#8217;s literally a reunion of all your loved ones
and a celebration of your life, up to that point.  Before the wedding, when you mention &#8220;Kate Elston, she&#8217;s in Meg&#8217;s
improv team&#8221; to your old roommates, you get a blank look and confusion.  After the wedding, it&#8217;s &#8220;Oh Kate, of course, we
should hang out.&#8221;  Anyways, hypothetically speaking, you enjoy parties, right?  Would you want to be totally
disconnected, marginalized, and kicked out of the planning of this party?  Of course not!  Don&#8217;t you care about who will
be invited, where it will be, what you will be doing?  The music that will played at the dance party?  The food that you
will eat?  The alcohol that you will drink? Do you like eating food and drinking beer?

Are you a grown man?  Are you good at planning things?  Do you have good decision making skills, are you good at
logistics?  Do you have good taste in music, food, and drink?

I basically suggest chucking the cultural script in the garbage bin and taking an active role in planning thew wedding.

Seriously though, men&#8217;s traditional strengths in planning & logistics have a huge role to play in creating a smoothly

People won&#8217;t know why your wedding felt good, but they will remember the absence of drama, the feeling of the care that
went into planning out each detail and having 
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Breakers Blues Band]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2013-06-20-the-breakers-blues-band"/>
    <updated>2013-06-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/the-breakers-blues-band</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[## “Play that thing!”

My stage presence was lacking.  I wasn't confident, and it showed.  I hunched over the guitar and stared at my hands.
I didn't smile, or ever look at the audience.

![breakers blues band LIVE album cover](/assets//cd-cover-nutinis.jpg "Breakers Blues Band LIVE 
album cover.")

Suddenly, Big Ray pointed his huge, meaty finger at me and shouted: “Kevin! PLAY THAT THING!”  Unsatisfied, he grabbed a 
spare guitar, and waded in to save me.

Ray’s guitar playing was not technically very good.  He played very simply, perhaps one note in rhythm, bending the 
string.

But his was totally different, and BETTER, than my playing.  He stood tall, he radiated confidence, he got louder, he 
got quieter, he looked at the audience, he smiled, he walked around and interacted with the drummer, with the bassist.

… I was by far my own worst critic.  Not everyone in the audience is musical; many can’t tell when you play wrong notes.
If you are smiling, and moving with the rhythm of the song, and sounds are coming from your guitar, all seems well.

It’s insulting if people come to see you play, and you don’t attempt to give a convincing performance by smiling and 
having good stage presence.

As with many other things in life, fake it till you make it.

Here’s a recording of us LIVE at Michigan Tech in the fall of 2003: 

<iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/87125122&amp;color=ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false"></iframe>


## The Beginning

![a group shot of the band in Hancock, Michigan](/assets//finder.jpg &#8220;Posing on the shore of the 
Portage in Hancock, MI.&#8221;)

The genesis of the Breakers Blues Band was the Michigan Tech Jazz program, lead by talented and wonderful Mike Irish.

I played the trumpet in these bands all through college.  But honestly, I hated the trumpet.  The musician must match 
the instrument.  The trumpet was everything I was not: brassy, loud, and over-confident.

The guitar, on the other hand, was fundamental, a rhythm instrument, it hung out in the background, keeping time and 
sounding groovy.  Much more my speed.  And I had been secretly playing the guitar (and the keyboard) since back in high 
school.  I taught myself, from ”The Complete Easy Beatles” with simplified chord diagrams.

My trumpet hatred must have been obvious, because in the fall of 2003, there was an opening in the MTU Jazz band for a 
guitarist, and Mike Irish gave the spot to me.  Thus my escape from the trumpet was accomplished.

Soon afterwards, there were a series of ‘jam sessions’ at the Motherlode cafe in downtown Houghton, which I shyly 
attended, although I rarely played.

One night a strange and interesting guy showed up:

It was a typical scene&#8212;the cafe full of stereotypical engineering students: shy, pale, slight, quiet, introverted, no 
one talking. Suddenly a tall, large, bearded, joyous man, leapt onto the stage with his saxophone, and passionately 
played, many notes, up and down the scale, moving his body with the rhythm, totally dominating the stage.

It was kind of shocking!  Such a lack of reserve!  Such confidence!  Did we like it?  Not sure.  Did we notice? 
Definitely.

This was &#8220;Big Ray&#8221; Haywood, and shortly afterwards, he joined the MTU jazz band.

The charts we were playing were good practice, and very beautiful.  But they were played straight from the charts, and 
solos were generally short, and somewhat rehearsed.

So, the opportunity was definitely there for smaller groups to form.  But we were lacking id, or primal desire.  If you 
had asked me if I wanted to form a band and go around gigging at bars, the idea wouldn&#8217;t have appealed to me.  But I 
didn&#8217;t know what I was missing.  ;)

However, Ray had a passion for the blues!  He had already been in a band (the Crossroads Blues Band with his brother and 
others) back at home in Detroit, and here, he saw opportunity: music-making, and money-making potential.


## The Perks of Fame

My junior year of college, I spent in Switzerland, learning French.  It was so amazing, it reset all my expectations.
When I came back, I felt really down.  I didn&#8217;t want to be at Michigan Tech.  For almost two years, I limped along, not 
enjoying much, frustrated, apathetic.

The root problem was my poor attitude.  However, time cured me eventually: I just got tired of feeling down all the 
time, and I decided to live again, in the here and now, where I was.

The Breakers Blues Band was an important part of this new period of self-growth: I &#8220;came out of my shell.&#8221; We were 
successful.  We had groupies.  Our shows were always full: we regularly drew crowds of more than 100 people.

Also, I had a responsibility to pull my weight.  This included having a good stage presence by appearing to enjoy 
myself.  At first it was an act.  But slowly, it became real.

I switched to the keyboard: piano blues can be so simple.  I got a lot better.  I learned how to solo: start off softly, 
build tension with a repetitive note or a riff, and then build a vocabulary of little tricks that sound cool. Our whole 
group got tighter: we were aggressively gigging: 2 shows a week for more than a year.  It was a whole epoch of 
my life.

We even had away shows, in Marquette and Copper Harbor.  We would throw afterparties and invite our fans to party with 
us.  And, at one of these shows, I met my first real girlfriend: Mandy Edwards.

![the band posing with a true Detroit Bluesmobile](/assets//car.jpg &#8220;Posing in front of our vintage
Bluesmobile.&#8221;)

![playing at the Ramada Waterfront Inn in Hancock, Michigan](/assets//finder1.jpg &#8220;Playing a solo at 
the Ramada Waterfront Inn in Hancock, Michigan&#8221;)

![Ray Haywood, Alan Cross, and Kevin Trowbridge](/assets//haha.jpg &#8220;Three friends sharing a laugh
while setting up for a show.&#8221;)

![my first real girlfriend, Mandy Edwards](/assets//kevin_and_mandy.jpg &#8220;My first real girlfriend,
Mandy Edwards.&#8221;)]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving to San Francisco]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2013-04-09-moving-to-san-francisco"/>
    <updated>2013-04-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/moving-to-san-francisco</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[In all honesty, the time I spent in Mountain View was one of the most lonely and empty of my life. That sounds pretty 
dire, I wasn't depressed or sad, but the time was -- basically empty. When I thought about it later, I couldn't remember 
much happening.

I spent many nights at home alone, saving money, drinking "Full Sail Amber Ale," eating pasta, and watching films from 
[Ebert's Great Movies list](http://www.rogerebert.com/great-movies). ;)

![new housemates!](/assets//ian_gunn_kevin_trowbridge_alex_mayer_3656a_housewarming_party.jpg "Ian, me, and Alex Mayer at the 3656A housewarming party on October 6th, 2006.")

My dear friend Dan Simon came to visit me and he hated, hated, hated Mountain View. He paraphrased the poem [Slough by 
John Betjeman](http://www-cdr.stanford.edu/intuition/Slough.html):

> &#8220;Come friendly bombs and fall on Mountain View!
> It isn&#8217;t fit for humans now,
> &#8230;
> Tinned fruit, tinned meat, tinned milk, tinned beans,
> Tinned minds, tinned breath.&#8221;

So, in my weekly meetings with my manager Stephanie Schoch, I started speaking about how I would like to move to San 
Francisco. Moving to San Francisco was a constant tension amongst the young folks at Ariba and on the Peninsula. The 
glittering city was the allure, but the cost was having to commute more than an hour every morning and evening.

Stephanie encouraged me, so I started taking the Caltrain up to SF on weekends and at night to go to apartment open 
houses. At first I fell into a common trap: renting a studio in the TenderKnob. When I told Stephanie about this, she 
said: &#8220;You&#8217;re not living in some bullshit studio in the Tenderloin! You&#8217;re living in the Mission!&#8221;

![best buddies!](/assets//kevin_and_gatsby_trowbridge.jpg &#8220;Gatsby and I at the housewarming party.&#8221;)

So I decided that I wanted to move in with a group of housemates in a shared apartment in the Mission. I went to a few 
open houses, but they were so competitive, and I hated feeling judged or having to &#8220;sell myself&#8221; to potential roommates.

So, I came up with a new plan. I found a &#8220;Roommate Meetup&#8221; group where people seeking roommates could meet, in a bar, 
and try to connect. The people who were seeking a place to live, wore red nametags, and those who were seeking people to 
move in with them, wore blue nametags.

The first few times I went, I wore the red nametag, indicating that I didn&#8217;t have an apartment and I was looking for 
someplace to live. But, since we were drinking in a bar, there was a blurry line between socializing, and actually 
looking for someone to move in with. It wasn&#8217;t very efficient and it was still very competitive.

So I had a brainstorm: I could wear a blue tag, and &#8220;pretend&#8221; that I already had an apartment, but I would actually be 
looking for people to join me, in looking for an empty apartment, to &#8220;found&#8221; together.

This was the winning approach. At the next meetup, wearing the blue nametag, I started meeting people. It was a little 
embarrassing to admit that I didn&#8217;t actually have a place, but I stood out, and I met other ambitious people.

![ian gunn at 3656a&#8217;s housewarming party](/assets//ian_gunn.jpg &#8220;Ian at the 3656A housewarming party on October 8th, 2006.&#8221;)

One of these people was Ian Gunn. He had a job with Google directly out of college and he was living in corporate housing 
in Mountain View. At first I didn&#8217;t like him, he seemed young, and pushy. We talked for a few minutes and then moved on.

However, at the end of the night, just as I was contemplating the long, uncomfortable ride home on Caltrain, he 
approached me again, saying that he had a car and he would give me a ride back to Mountain View. I somewhat 
half-heartedly agreed.

But during the 45 minute car ride south, we started talking, and I realized that I really liked Ian Gunn. He was smart, 
and funny, and a good guy. We decided that we would be partners and look for an apartment together.

This was the beginning of an even more epic stage, which would be so boring to encyclopedically relate, but suffice it 
to say that we needed a 3rd roommate to join, who we found eventually: Alex Mayer. Using his skills with the ladies, 
Ian met a real estate agent, Tatianna, who eventually gave us the keys to a quasi-shitty apartment with a great 
location: 3656A 20th Street.

![san francisco skyline](/assets//3656a_back_porch_san_francisco_skyline.jpg &#8220;The view of SF downtown from 3656A&#8217;s back porch the night of the housewarming party.&#8221;)

Alex Mayer was gone in Thailand when we needed to sign the lease, so we called hotels in Thailand and faxed the 
documents to him there. On the night we needed him to actually sign the lease, he was gone on a 50 mile bike ride, and 
Ian and I found ourselves driving aimlessly around Palo Alto, because he had agreed to meet us at a certain place on 
the side of the road, at a certain time, to sign the lease. It was hilarious and very memorable.

But finally we were in! We got a place and we all moved in together on September 28th, 2006. It was one of the best 
decisions I had made in my life, thus far, because going forward, so many good things flowed from this.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brutus, Michigan From 1930 on, an Interview With Elmer G. Wurst]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2009-09-05-an-interview-with-elmer-g-wurst-brutus-michigan-from-1930-on"/>
    <updated>2009-05-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/brutus-michigan-from-1930-on-an-interview-with-elmer-g-wurst</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[I grew up in a very rural area of Northern Lower Michigan (near Petoskey, Michigan).  When I was young, I was very 
influenced by my maternal grandfather (Elmer G. Wurst) who was an amateur genealogist and historian.  Elmer lived in 
Northern Michigan his entire life (until his death at 88 in 2004), and had an amazing knowledge of people and events in 
that area!

Perhaps there is a historian / genealogist gene, because I also have a great interest in history.  I anticipated my 
grandfather's death and always wanted to somehow capture his knowledge - unfortunately I was too shy and inexperienced 
to ever formally interview him and record our conversations (a mistake I greatly regret!).

![elmer wurst being interviewed](/assets//2002maygrampas-interview.jpg "Elmer Wurst interviewed by 
Kayla Williams and Donna Steward in 2002.")

Luckily, two local schoolgirls outdid me!  These two were researching the history of Brutus, Michigan for a school project.  On March 12th, 2002, they interviewed grandpa and recorded their conversation.  (Their names are Kayla Williams and Donna Steward, along with their teacher, Sally Smith).  While I was at home this Christmas 2008 my mother (Janet Trowbridge) showed me the tape which she had kept.  I transferred it to the computer and - thought I'd put it up here on the blog, the better to share the information with my family (interested in Elmer Wurst), and others who are interested in the history of Northern Michigan.

Listen to the interview (57min)

<iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/156360896%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-XvPrM&amp;color=ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false"></iframe>

It&#8217;s a bit hard to make out everything at speed, so (for my own curiosity and your benefit!) I created a transcript. 
You&#8217;ll understand much more if you read along with the interview.

### Interview regarding history of Brutus, MI and specifically its train depot.

* Date:  March 12th, 2002
* Location: dining room of EW&#8217;s house&#8230;
* Present:
  - Students:  Kayla Williams and Donna Steward
  - **SS**: Sally Smith, teacher at Alanson Middle School
  - **EW**: Elmer Wurst
  - **JT**: Janet Trowbridge, Elmer Wurst&#8217;s daughter

Audible in background:

* EW&#8217;s finch.
* Scanner (EW loved to listen to the local authorities&#8217; radio discussions.)

&#8212;&#8211;

#### My mother emailed me these details about the interview

Hey Kev,

The 2 girls names were Kayla Williams (my cousin, Bruce Johansen&#8217;s step-daughter) & Donna Stewart.
Their teacher was Sally Smith.  They had to give an oral report in front of their class and I&#8217;m not
sure what they did at the Waterfront Museum in Petoskey.  They probably had to do something.  It was
a pretty big assignment for the whole class & I&#8217;m sure took the whole marking period to put it
together.  I&#8217;ll try to find out how to get in tough with Mrs. Smith & get back with you with more
details.

His bird was a finch and yes it did chirp constantly.  One can actually hear the ambiance of his house, can&#8217;t you?  Also, I think the scanner went off a couple times.  Brings back lots of memories.

I&#8217;ll try to find the picture of the girls with their train station soon & send it to you.

Love,
Mama


## The Transcript

&#8212; 0:00 START TRANSCRIPT &#8212;

Students: This is Kayla Williams and Donna Steward.  We are interviewing Mr. Elmer Wurst, who grew up in Michigan, Brutus Michigan.  Today is March 12th, 2002.

EW:  Ok

SS:  You wanna start with your questions, ladies?

Student: Um, I was wondering - like - do you know any important facts that happened in Brutus?

EW: (Pauses) &#8230; well (laughs) &#8230; I wasn&#8217;t there when the Purple Inn burnt, but I was there for a while when it was goin&#8217;.

Student: Do you know, like, if there was any bombings or anything?

EW:  Well, uh, that one time there was a, they built a catholic church in there, and the first day they were supposed to have a service in it, lightning hit it and burned it down.

&#8212; 1:00m &#8212;

(Exclamations)

SS: Oh my god!

EW: (laughter) And they never rebuilt it, never tried anything again - that was the end of it!

SS: And this was the catholic church?

EW: Yeah.

Student:  Do you know anything about the Mennonites that came to Brutus?

EW:  yeah, first they came up in here, in this country right up here, around Ayr, and then they went over to the Mennonite settlement over there, east of brutus.

&#8212; 2:00m &#8212;

SS:  You mentioned that you knew about the Purple Inn when it was running.  Were any of the relatives &#8230; sorry, you two ladies, if I&#8217;m interjecting once in a while&#8230; were the original families still operating it when you knew about it?

EW:  Yeah, Mrs. Perfore (?) was there.  See he was the sherriff, and ugh, he got shot back in 1922 and died.  And then she ran the Inn there, the rest of the time that I was there, in &#8216;34, and then she moved in to Petoskey from there.  And she was &#8230; well, she was in that &#8230; buliding right in there by the tennis courts - you go up on top of the hill, way up on top of the hill &#8230; well, the tennis courts ain&#8217;t there any more!!

SS:  Well that&#8217;s ok.  You mean, her house?

EW:  No, she started one in there.

SS:  Oh, she did!

EW: Yeah, uh huh.

SS:  Oh, my goodness.

&#8212; 3:00m &#8212;

EW: Yeah, this is &#8230; (indicating map) &#8230; that&#8217;s the inn there &#8230; that&#8217;s the depot.

SS:  Oh, my goodness, look at that folks &#8230; oh, how wonderful!

SS:  Did she have, were there children?  Did the Purples have children?  There was Nelly, and then, Will?

&#8230;

Ok, you know more than &#8230;

EW:  Uh - what the heck was?  Mitchley was their father, and he lived with them, and he lived to be over a hundred years old.  I never knew him, uh, but I knew of him.

&#8212; 4:00m &#8212;

Students:  Do you know how, do you know how Mrs. Purple died?

Ew:  No &#8230; no, uhh, she died &#8230; just about the time the (&#8216;cut off in Petoskey there&#8217;) &#8230; (&#8216;moved the tennis courts over by the bridge&#8217; - guess) &#8230; she died just about then &#8230; my wife was working at her place.

SS:  How many meals did they serve, when your wife was working there &#8230; was there, like three meals?

EW:  I don&#8217;t think they had boarders there.

SS:  They did not have borders?

EW:  I don&#8217;t think so &#8230; they could have had, but I don&#8217;t know of any of them.

SS:  So it was primarily run as a restaurant then?

&#8212; 5:00m &#8212;

EW:  yeah, but it was a little bit exclusive

SS:  Ohh, see that&#8217;s what I thought &#8230; so it was exclusive?

EW:  Yeah, the Burt Lake resorters would come in there a lot.

SS:  Very interesting &#8230; the Burt Lake resorters &#8230; then, when Mrs. Purple served as the hostess, I guess you would say, for the inn - see, we&#8217;re going to do costumes at the museum &#8230;

EW:  (laughs)

SS:  And I was trying to think of &#8230; of course it would still be turn of the century &#8230; and I was wondering if she dressed up, or if she wore an apron, of if there were any colors to her and her wait staff?

EW:  Gosh, I couldn&#8217;t tell you.  (laughs)

SS:  Ok, I just wondered &#8230;

EW:  No, I couldn&#8217;t &#8230; they all dressed up though &#8230;

SS:  They all dressed up.

EW:  Yeah, they all dressed up.  Uh &#8230; but they were all well dressed, and served like &#8230; were serving rich people.

&#8212; 6:00m &#8212;

SS:  What were some of their favorite meals, or specialities, I should say?

EW:  I couldn&#8217;t tell you that!  (laughs)

SS:  We got one recipie from Jan Smith at Stanford&#8217;s for a &#8216;Purple Inn&#8217; &#8230; was is Huckleberry?

Students:  Yeah, Huckleberry cake.

EW:  Yeah, that could be.

SS:  I just didn&#8217;t know if there were any others specials, people would go to the Purple Inn, for you know, like they go to Bob&#8217;s Place for &#8230; roast &#8230;

Students:  There&#8217;s umm .. she made Chicken dinners for a dollar a plate.

EW:  Ya, yeah, she made Chicken dinners, and fish &#8230; and she used to sell a lot of Indian baskets too &#8230; the Indians sold her a lot of baskets.

SS:  That&#8217;d be quill baskets too, or just the &#8230; ?

EW:  Yeah, quill and reed baskets.

SS:  Oh good, quill and the reed baskets &#8230; oh, that&#8217;s great.  And the Inn was purple?

&#8212; 7:00m &#8212;

EW:  No!  It was brown!

(general laughter)

SS:  It was brown!  Ohhh, ok, that&#8217;s what I wondered.

Students:  Oh, on the internet it said it was painted purple.

SS:  It did say that it was purple.

Janet Trowbridge (daughter of EW):  Oh my goodness!  Well, that&#8217;s just their name, right?

SS:  Oh, well, there we go, we&#8217;re clarifying.

EW:  Yeah, that was their name, ya.

SS:  So, do you know if there were any &#8230; when you say that it was the wealthy people from Burt Lake that came &#8230; were there any other famous people you know of that may of attended, the Purple Inn?

EW:  (sighs)  Gosh - I don&#8217;t know, probably, there must have been, because there was some real, big names out there, in the Burt Lake.

SS:  Ok, so maybe in the Burt lake community &#8230; (to students)  Go ahead &#8230; I&#8217;ve kind of taken over, and I didn&#8217;t mean to&#8230;

&#8212; 8:00m &#8212;

Students:  This may be out of our way or anything, but do you know any of the major imports or exports that they had?  Or did they not have them back then?

EW:  Well, they made broom handles &#8230; uh, they had a regular handle mill there.  And they done a lot of lumbering &#8230; potatoes &#8230; they had a pickle factory there, they made pickles.  And they sent a lot of potatoes to Ohio &#8230; uh, Israel Eby was one of the Mennonites, and he bought a truck to start hauling &#8230; down south, and he got kicked out of the church for, (laughs) driving a truck!

SS:  Oh for driving a truck, that&#8217;s interesting, (to students) did you hear that?

&#8212; 9:00m &#8212;

SS:  How interesting!  And he&#8217;d go all the way to Ohio?  With his potatoes.  And this was a Mr. Eby?  Is this Silas?

EW:  Israel.

SS:  (to students) Is there a Silas?  Cyrus, maybe?  Cyrus.

EW:  Yeah, there&#8217;s a Cyrus Eby.  Cyrus Eby is &#8230; two miles north, and half a mile east, of there &#8230; the old Eby farm over there.

SS:  Ok.  So Israel (to students) just like the country.  Israel Eby.  And he got kicked out of the church for doing that.  See, those are fun stories.  (laughs)  Not for Mr. Eby, but&#8230;

EW:  They didn&#8217;t believe in anything modern, at all.  They was, at that time, they was &#8230; nothing modern.  They couldn&#8217;t drive a car, they coulnd&#8217;t have a tractor &#8230; anything.  &#8230;  Amos Gregory - almost got kicked out - they changed, just about the time he made himself a homemade tractor &#8230;

&#8212; 10:00m &#8212;

SS:  (gasps)

EW: (laughs) They didn&#8217;t like that at all!

SS:  Are you girls clear on what the Mennonites believe?

Students:  Pretty much, I think.

SS:  Because I think Mr. Wurst would know a lot about that too.

EW:  They &#8230; they moved from up in this neighborhood, and, uh, went over there, and &#8230; well, we used to pick up cream over there - my dad worked for a cream station in Petoskey - and we used to pick up cream all through there, and well, that was in &#8216;27, and we used to pick up a lot of cream over there.  And, all the way down &#8230; well that would probably be another product that was sold as cream.

SS:  Cream?

EW:  Or butter.

&#8212; 11:00m &#8212;

SS:  Ahh, there&#8217;s a picture at the Alanson depot with the cream buckets out front.

EW:  Yeah.

Students:  Umm, do you know the Brutus&#8217;s true colors?  Like &#8230; when I was first &#8230; umm?  The depot?

EW:  (laughs)  Well, same as in Alanson, it was the color green.

SS:  It was sort of an Army green?

EW:  Yeah.

SS:  And it did have red trim, by any chance?

EW:  I don&#8217;t think so.

SS:  It was just all green?

EW:  It was a darker green trim then the [main body color].

SS:  So it was different shades of green?

EW:  Um hmm.

Students:  What about the roof?

EW:  That was wood shingles.

SS:  Oh, wood shingles?  So it would have been cedar?

EW:  Yeah

SS:  Cedar shingles, which would have been a brown color?

EW:  Yeah, everything was cedar shingles them days.

SS:  That&#8217;s right (to students), and I will have to explain it to you.

&#8212; 12:00m &#8212;

SS:  That they&#8217;re wood instead of today &#8230; today we have asphalt, right, asphalt, and another new fabric out for shingles &#8230; I want to say, fiberglass &#8230;

EW:  Yeah, fiberglass, and then (unintelligible) &#8230; they might of had some &#8230; I don&#8217;t know, they might of had, they didn&#8217;t have tar on the roofs at all.  But &#8230; I, yes, the Smiths had a shingle mill - so they made shingles right there.

SS:  So they made cedar shingles &#8230; they just cut cedar shingles at Smith&#8217;s mill (to students) are you aware of Smith&#8217;s mill?

EW:  Schmidt, Schmidth

SS:  S C H M I D T ?

EW:  Yeah

SS:  (to students)  You might ask a question about Hinkley&#8217;s?

EW:  Oh, that was the handle mill.  I think &#8230; I&#8217;m not sure about it, but I think that that, uh &#8230; (indicating on map) yeah, it must &#8230; I think that this was probably Hinkley&#8217;s house there, that&#8217;s &#8230; uh &#8230;

&#8212; 13:00m &#8212;

SS:  Right here?

EW:  Yeah.

SS:  Ok &#8230; (to students) Do you have this picture here? &#8230; And then the depot?

EW:  Yeah, the depot was down to the end down here &#8230; the depot was right, to the &#8230; right there.

SS:  Oh, I see, and this was Purple Inn?

EW:  Yeah.

&#8212; 14:00m &#8212;

SS:  Oh my.

EW:  And this was Wagley&#8217;s store &#8230; this was &#8230; Wagley was, well, they were probably some of the first people in Northern Michigan.  They had a sawmill, and they had a boat in Cross Village.  And &#8230; uh, in fact, he used the boat to go to Beaver Island, when they kicked the Mormans off &#8230; or, not the Mormans, but King Strang off of the island &#8230;

[JT: notes that the full name of the store owner was &#8216;Lynn Wagley&#8217;]

SS:  King Strang, oh my goodness!  (to students) I&#8217;m sorry &#8230; [I&#8217;m] talking too much, go ahead?

(general laughter)

Students: Umm, did the Hinkley brothers own the Butter bowl?  (?)

EW:  Yeah, in Alanson &#8230; I don&#8217;t think they had a Butter bowl mill in Brutus &#8230; maybe they did?  I wouldn&#8217;t say for sure.

&#8212; 15:00m &#8212;

Students:  We&#8217;re going to have to check over our internet stuff.

SS:  We have found some problems with things on the internet &#8230; with the wrong location, we had to have it verified by the museum - who was not happy with &#8230; of course, incorrect information &#8230; it wasn&#8217;t done by the museum, but somebody else.  See that&#8217;s why these interviews are so priceless.

EW:  Uh &#8230; all that was there when I remember, was just a big sawdust pile (?) &#8230; a sawdust pile as big as this house.  That was all I ever seen of &#8230;

&#8212; 16:00m &#8212;

SS:  Did sawdust piles that tall sometimes catch fire?

EW:  Yeah, I imagine that them was hauled away for bedding and stuff like that, because it dissapeared, and I never seen any more of it.

SS:  That was the end of it.

SS:  (to students) You were asking about the Butter bowl, the Butter bowl mill?  Good!

Students:  Do you know any other businesses that were up there?

EW:  (sighs) No, they had a sawmill there &#8230; that cut lumber.  &#8216;Cause where my grandfather&#8217;s built their new house, why they hauled logs down there to the sawmill &#8230; one tree built the whole house!

SS:  Oh my!  One, did you hear that, one tree!

Students:  That was ours.

SS:  That was yours?!

Students: No, that &#8230; our house was like that too.

SS:  Built by one tree, with one tree?  Isn&#8217;t that fascinating?

&#8212; 17:00m &#8212;

EW:  They sold two logs off from, besides that, to the sawmill &#8230; uh, they couldn&#8217;t even get them in the door to the sawmill - so, they drilled a hole in &#8216;em, put a stick of dynamite in to &#8216;em, and blowed &#8216;em all to pieces!

JT:  Oh my goodness!

(gasps)

EW:  And then, the other log &#8230; well, they made the hole bigger, so they&#8217;d get the log in!

SS:  Oh my gosh!

(laughs)

EW:  But it was a tree that was in a difficult place to get to, and if they cut it, it was going to go down into Maple river &#8230; awful steep bank &#8230; now, how my grandfather got it out, I don&#8217;t know, but it went &#8230; two 16-foot logs, and then it branched, and they cut four sixteen foot logs out of the branches!  So it must have been a monster of a tree.

&#8212; 18:00m &#8212;

EW:  And the whole Mennonite settlement over there was &#8230; great big pine trees.  I don&#8217;t know &#8230; (to daughter Janet)  Are there still stumps over there? &#8230; Hard to know, you&#8217;d have to go down by Gregory&#8217;s?

JT:  Down by Gregory&#8217;s?  Like south from the Dam site?

EW:  Yeah.  That&#8217;d be the first tract (unintelligible).

JT:  Well, I don&#8217;t know &#8230; (laughs) I don&#8217;t know!  &#8230; if I remember seeing any stumps, I&#8217;m not really sure&#8230;  You mean all those open fields were trees?  Were woods?

EW:  Yeah, oh yeah.  I don&#8217;t know how they ever planted anything in where those pine stumps were.

JT:  Oh my gosh!

&#8212; 19:00m &#8212;

EW:  Yeah, them were great big monster stumps like that, and &#8230; of course, pine doesn&#8217;t rot very fast, and they was hard to get out!  (laughs)

SS:  (to students)  Other questions?

Students:  I, like, have a question, but I&#8217;m, kinda like, not too sure about it?

SS:  What&#8217;s it have to do with?

Students:  I have no clue!

EW:  (laughs)

SS:  Okay &#8230;

EW:  What is it?

JT:  Spit it out!

(laughter)

Students:  Um &#8230; do you like, in Brutus, do you know how people acted towards each other?  Like &#8230;

&#8212; 20:00m &#8212;

SS:  The personality of the community, what people were like.

EW:  It was all &#8230; they all seemed friendly, yeah, it was all friendly &#8230;   Uh, when I was up there in &#8216;34, I stayed with my grandfolks for two years &#8230; and, uh - everybody went to the store pretty near every night, and sat there, and talked &#8230; and (laughs) &#8230; they had a &#8230; it was real friendly.

SS:  Sociable?

SS:  The Brutus school only went to the fourth grade?

EW:  At that time, yeah.

SS:  I see.

&#8212; 21:00m &#8212;

Students:  Umm, didn&#8217;t one of the Brills used to, like, own one of the halfway houses or something like that (unintelligible)?

EW:  Yeah, yeah &#8230; uh, it was, let&#8217;s see, (to daughter Janet) What&#8217;s that road past (unintelligible)&#8217;s up there?

JT:  Maple River Road

EW:  Yeah, Maple River Road &#8230; after you cross the river where the gold course is now.

JT:  Where the &#8230; what&#8217;s that called, the new one?

EW:  Yeah, the new golf course.

JT:  It&#8217;s past the three cornered stone church, turn right off the highway, and you go down over the river, and that &#8230; I don&#8217;t know what that new golf course is &#8230;

Students:  Isn&#8217;t it like hidden river or something?

JT:  Yeah.

SS:  Hidden Valley?  No?

(laughter, more names)

EW:  But you see the stagecoach road used to come from Harbor, 

&#8212; 22:00m &#8212;

&#8230; and it&#8217;d go through there and it went through the school forest over here, in back of Alanson, by the cemetery, and then it went up, and went across by Schmidt&#8217;s, and turned north, and there&#8217;s still a piece of road that &#8230; after you cross Brutus road, that&#8217;s called &#8216;stagecoach road&#8217; and, it crossed down through Brill&#8217;s, and it crossed the river &#8230; and they a stop, a layover there &#8230;

EW:  And my grandparents ran it for a year or so up there, the stagecoach stop, on the way to Cheboygan.  And, that&#8217;s probably, that&#8217;s probably the last time it run, was when they &#8230;

&#8212; 23:00m &#8212;

SS: They operated it.  And were they Wursts also?

EW:  No, they was Burgesses.

SS:  Burgesses, B U R &#8230; B U R G E S

EW: S S

SS: Oh, Burgess!  Ok, sure - isn&#8217;t there a Burgess road?

EW:  Out by &#8230; Sturgeon Bay &#8230;

SS:  Yeah!  I&#8217;ve seen a Burgess &#8230; isn&#8217;t that funny, I can see the sign &#8230;

EW:  No, not Sturgeon Bay, Bay Shore.

SS:  Bay Shore, Ok.

Students:  Do you know of any forms of entertainment that was on the train?

EW:  That was on the train?  (laughs)  Nope &#8230; there was a lot of trains, though!  When I was up &#8230; it could be as high as &#8230; one every hour.

(gasps)

EW:  Goin&#8217; one way or the other.

&#8212; 24:00m &#8212;

SS:  And were they all passenger trains, or?

EW:  No - well, there were passenger trains, and then they&#8217;d have freight trains too.  See, they hauled all the Iron Ore and stuff on the train, after the lakes started freezing.  Well they was all pulled by train &#8230; there was 40 cars to a train.

SS:  Right &#8230; (to students) you have that down?  (Unintelligible)  (to EW)  So sorry &#8230;  And you said Iron Ore, coming from Mackinaw?

EW:  No, coming from up across the Straights.

SS:  So, I&#8217;m trying to figure out the route &#8230; so if it went through Brutus?

EW:  Eh, it came all the way across the lake, from up in the straights &#8230; there was a boat that hauled the &#8230;

SS:  Wawanum (?) &#8230; (to students) that&#8217;s what you need to know &#8230; and I&#8217;ve got the book at school &#8230; the Wawanum then would load the Iron ore on to a train &#8230;

&#8212; 25:00m &#8212;

EW:  Well, no they&#8217;d go clear from &#8230; (to JT) where is that from, Kevin?  (Your humble transcriptionist, KT, son of JT, grandson of EW - I went to college in Houghton, MI, in the Keweenaw Penninsula.)

JT:  Where Kevin is?  The Keweenaw peninsula?  So they&#8217;d come down Lake Superior &#8230;

SS:  The train would?

JT:  The boat.

EW:  Well, no - up in the wintertime&#8230;

JT:  Oh, the train&#8230;

SS:  The train would come all the way from Lake Superior?

EW:  Yup.

SS:  With Iron Ore &#8230; (to students) are you writing this down, ladies?  (laughter)  This is really good!  This is the first we&#8217;ve come across &#8230; (to students) did you read this anywhere?

Students: Yup.

SS:  Okay &#8230; they&#8217;ve been doing a super job, by the way!  I just thought &#8230; maybe that got away from me.  (to students) All the way from the Keweenaw peninulsa, they would haul Iron ore!

Students:  How do you spell that?

SS:  IRON, and then &#8216;Ore&#8217;

Students:  No&#8230;

JT:  Keweenaw?

(general laughter, EW especially)

SS:  K, double E, W A N A U, isn&#8217;t it?  No?

JT:  There&#8217;s a W E in it.

SS:  There&#8217;s a W?  You all would no more than I would &#8230;

JT:  (unintelligible)

&#8212; 26:00m &#8212;

SS:  (to students) N A W

Students:  Do you know what this is for?

SS:  We keep seeing this on roofs!  With the ladder &#8230; and the little steps?

EW:  Well, that was probably &#8230; uh &#8230; whether they had stops there or not?

SS:  Was this a sign?

EW:  That&#8217;s a sign, yeah.

SS:  Okay, and so they would have to change that sign?

EW:  Mmm hmm &#8230; they had &#8230;

SS:  And that would tell you?

EW:  Gonna stop, or go, or whether they had passengers or not.  At that time, you could take the can or cream down anyplace to the railroad tracks, and they&#8217;d stop and pick it up.

SS:  Oh, a can of cream.

EW:  Yeah!

(laughter)

SS:  (to students)  Go for you, reading that.  See, we&#8217;ve been all looking at those (unintelligible) steps and we thought that maybe was to change the sign, but sometimes the steps would be there, and there&#8217;d be no sign, so we were sort of confused.

EW:  And sometimes they had the, uh &#8230; (to JT) you get it?

&#8212; 27:00m &#8212;

JT:  Yeah, Keweenaw &#8230; K E W &#8230; okay &#8230; two Es &#8230; N A W &#8230; spelled, K E W E E N A W.

(girlish laugh from students)

SS:  Oh, it&#8217;s Whee!  Key - wee - naw!

EW:  Yeah, Kee -  Whee &#8230;

SS:  Okay &#8230; so the trains would come through with the Iron Ore &#8230; and you were asking, you know &#8230; what other products passed through?  It would be mostly the Iron Ore during the winter months.

EW:  Yeah &#8230; and they hauled cream outta there.

SS:  And the cream.

EW:  Yeah.

SS:  Another one that&#8217;s fascinating&#8230;

EW:  Yeah, they hauled a lot of cream &#8230; what was that &#8230; cedar &#8230; cedar valley?

&#8212; 28:00m TAPE FLIPS &#8212;

SS:  The &#8230; umm, (to students) do you wanna ask about &#8230; I don&#8217;t wanna ask &#8230; do you have any more questions?  What about &#8230; the passenger?  Go ahead.

Students:  It&#8217;s not really a question, but it&#8217;s something Mr. Woodrove told us &#8230; he, and a couple kids from our kids interviewed him for Oden &#8230; he thought that the steps on our roof was for mail?  Do you know if that was also a possibility for it, like &#8230; do you know if?

EW:  They&#8217;d keep right on going without stopping!

SS:  Yes.

EW:  Yeah &#8230; they had a hanger there that they hung a mailbag on.  And they&#8217;d just stick out an arm (creak of chair, presumably miming motion) and snatch her right in!

(general laughter)

SS:  Just had to remember to let go!

Students:  So they just like, stuck it out, while the train was moving?

EW:  Yeah!

Students:  Whoo!

EW:  Yeah, yup.  They used to do that alot, actually &#8230;

SS:  That wouldn&#8217;t be on that same sign &#8230; that would be on a separate hook?

&#8212; 29:00m &#8212;

EW:  Yeah, yeah, that would be a hook.

SS:  A separate hook that would come out.  (to students)  Do you want to ask about the passenger pigeons?

Students:  Do you know if the passenger pigeons were up there or not?  Around in there?

EW:  No, I lived a little far north for the passenger pigeons &#8230; uhh, passenger pigeons was more in by, uh &#8230; oh, you know where Petoskey Sands is &#8230;

SS: Sure.

EW:  Yeah &#8230; in there &#8230; in that country was where the passenger pigeons was.

SS:  Okay, sort of on that state road, or by the Petoskey park, state park.

EW:  Yeah, yeah.  They killed thousands of those &#8230; just barrels of tham.

SS:  We read &#8230; one train called 450 thousand &#8230; that was not unusual for it to be like that (unintelligible).

EW:  Right - they didn&#8217;t even stop to cut their heads off!  They bit their heads off!

Student:  Ewwww!!!

&#8212; 30:00m &#8212;

(laughter)

JT:  That&#8217;s not a nice thing to record!

EW:  Yeah - they&#8217;d capture them things, and they&#8217;d bite their heads off, and throw &#8216;em in the barrel.

Student:  Woo!!  That&#8217;s something I didn&#8217;t need to know!

SS:  We&#8217;re gonna tell the girls from &#8230; we have a Kegomic depot &#8230; by the tannery &#8230; wouldn&#8217;t that be from around the same area, or no?

EW:  Yeah &#8230; that&#8217;d be the same &#8230;

SS:  Interesting fact for them!  Oh my goodness!

Students:  Oh the internet site &#8230; did they, um, punch out their eyes also?  Like, punch out their eyes.

SS:  Oh!

EW:  I don&#8217;t know about that &#8230;

SS:  Was that on the internet?

Students:  Yeah - well, actually it came out of that passenger pigeon book.

SS:  Oh really &#8230; that&#8217;s might be &#8230; that was the one from the historical society.

EW:  It&#8217;s entirely possible!

Students:  It&#8217;s nasty!

SS:  Ohh &#8230; yes!

&#8212; 31:00m &#8212;

EW:  Well, they was &#8230; they was a lot of passenger pigeons &#8230; they said the sky was black!  They couldn&#8217;t see hardly.

Students:  For hours.

SS:  Yes, one report says they had to light their lanterns &#8230; because at one point, one day, the sky got so dark.

Students:  Ok, so they just like &#8230; like &#8230; bit their heads off, like &#8230; did they even think?

SS:  How did they grab them, you mean?  They were that approachable?

EW:  Yeah, they would take them out of the net.

SS:  Ohh &#8230; now where were these nets &#8230; you mean, they had these big nets?

EW:  Yeah, that they shot &#8230; they&#8217;d wait till they landed, and then they&#8217;d shoot these nets out over them, and catch them, and then they&#8217;d get in there, and grab them just as fast as they could.

SS:  So were the nets shot out, like a gun?

EW:  Well, it was &#8230; I don&#8217;t really know how they &#8230; I think it was &#8230;

SS:  I wonder how they did it?  I thought they shot them out of the sky, but no.

EW:  No.

&#8212; 32:00m &#8212;

SS:  Oh my &#8230;

EW:  It was netting.

SS:  (to students) Ok, I&#8217;m sorry ladies &#8230; go ahead.

Students:  (amongst selves) They didn&#8217;t go through our depot &#8230; oh yeah.

SS:  Train lines, is that what you were going to ask?

Student:  No, she was thinking about the double train.

Student:  Umm &#8230; how many railroad lines were there going through our depot?

Student (amongst selves):  Three.

Student (amongst selves):  Just makin&#8217; sure.

EW:  I think there was only one there in (Brutus?).  Uhh &#8230; there was a spur off of the side of it &#8230; I think one of them pictures has got a uh &#8230;

Student:  One of the pictures has it, and it looks like there&#8217;s three of them.

EW:  Yeah &#8230; see, there&#8217;s a train off in back of the depot &#8230; and the tracks actually went in front of the depot.

SS:  Did uh &#8230; we have had a lot of talk about &#8230; in our research about the dummy train.  Did the dummy train come to Brutus, that you know of?  We have the answers to that, we think.

&#8212; 33:00m &#8212;

EW:  Yeah, I think it went all the way to Mackinac &#8230; but not all the time.

SS:  So when it went to Mackinac would it automatically make a stop in Brutus?  Not necessarily.

EW:  Well, if there was somebody on it that wanted to get off, yeah.

SS:  So they could have just swung it around, and backed it up?

EW:  Uh &#8230; I don&#8217;t think them things even turned around &#8230; I think they&#8217;d &#8230; go to Harbor Springs, and then back up to the Tannery, and then go off towards Brutus &#8230; I know they went to Conway, and uh &#8230; the first railroad went as far as Conway, pulled by horses.

SS:  And were those wood rails?

EW:  Yeah.

SS:  Okay &#8230;

Students:  (overwhelmed sound)

&#8212; 34:00m &#8212;

SS:  They&#8217;re getting organized over here &#8230; actually they&#8217;re very organized, I&#8217;m real pleased.

Students:  This may be out of proportion but, um, do you have any idea of how many people would work at the depot?  Like, an estimate?

EW:  I don&#8217;t think there was very many worked at the depot in Brutus, maybe two.

SS:  Two?  Telegraph operator?

EW:  Yeah, and the depot agent.

SS:  I&#8217;m sorry, what was that?

EW:  Agent &#8230; they called him the depot agent.  Yeah.  He uh, took care of the mail, and stuff like that &#8230; stuff that went in and out of the train.

SS:  Oh!  (to students)  See, there you go, that answered what his job was.

&#8212; 35:00m &#8212;

Student:  What?

SS:  That he would &#8230; oversee the mail, and what went in and out of the trains.

EW:  Uh huh, they would load it on wagons &#8230; and, um, I remember when &#8230; after what, William Lagley (?) died, why the Evanses &#8230; took care of it, and there wasn&#8217;t even an agent there then, I don&#8217;t believe, in the depot, but they had &#8230; a four-wheeled wagon that they hauled back and forth and took care of the mail, and that stuff.  And uh &#8230;

Student:  (looking at notebook) Oh, I think we know that one &#8230;  (to EW)  Um, how did communication take place, like, between cities.

&#8212; 36:00m &#8212;

EW:  They had telephone, uh, there&#8217;s still a Brutus telephone, still owned (laughs) by the separate community &#8230; uh, but they was telephones all over, I can remember telephone poles &#8230;

SS:  Crank?

EW:  Yeah, we had a crank telephone here, for a long while &#8230; and, uh &#8230; in fact this one (refering to telephone in EW&#8217;s house), uh, was put in privately, and uh, run to the bottom, well - pretty-near-to Conway &#8230; and then they sold it to Bell telephone company, for a dollar (laughs) &#8230; and this is the only Petoskey phone &#8230;

SS:  Oh my gosh!

EW:  At that time, it was the only phone around here &#8230;

Student 1:  Do you know why our depot was placed where it is?

Student 2:  We believe it was because of lumber, but &#8230;

&#8212; 37:00m &#8212;

EW:  Yeah, well, it was lumber, and that&#8217;s where a little town was &#8230; and, well, wherever the service went, was where they &#8230;  they was, they was good on service!  The depots, the trains was excellent, gave excellent service!  And they run strictly on time, they was right on the minute &#8230; you could depend on &#8216;em, you could set your clocks by &#8216;em.

Student:  Do you, um, know how much a train ticket cost back then?

EW:  We used to go from Petoskey to Brutus, or Alanson, for twenty-five cents.  I think Alanson was fifteen.

[Gasps, folks are amazed by concept of inflation, EW laughs.]

&#8212; 38:00m &#8212;

Student:  So back then, people, like didn&#8217;t get, like pay much, like, my mom said that about like, when my grandma was a kid, a loaf of bread cost three pennies.

EW:  (thinks)  We&#8217;d pay a dime for it, I don&#8217;t know &#8230; I don&#8217;t suppose I can remember it any cheaper than that, but we used to pay that for it.

Student:  Like, do you know how much people made per hour?

EW:  (sighs, reflects)  Well, in 1929, before the depression hit, my dad was gettin&#8217; a dollar, err, five dollars a day.  And, before that was, that year was over, he was gettin&#8217; three.  (laughs)  So, before, after, before that winter was over he was going and ridin&#8217; to Cross Village in an open truck and shoveling show for three dollars an hour, err, day!

&#8212; 39:00m &#8212;

SS:  Three dollars a day, shoveling snow!?

EW:  Yeah &#8230; and, uh, it was a long cold trip, riding in an open truck!  That was &#8230; &#8216;30, &#8216;31.  They, uh &#8230; a dollar a day, they worked a long time doing it and got a dollar a day.

Student:  When did you move to Brutus, or did you not move to Brutus?

EW:  I was born in Brutus!

Student:  Oh, you were born in Brutus?

EW:  I was born in Brutus on Red School Road, right by the &#8230;

Students:  (cute laugh/gasp) That&#8217;s where I live!  Do you know Bruce Johansen?

EW:  Sure!

Student:  He&#8217;s your uncle, or, you were his uncle?

EW:  Yeah, ya, ya.

Student:  He&#8217;s my stepdad.

&#8212; 40:00m &#8212;

EW:  Okay!  (realizes he is related to this child)  We know each other then.

SS:  See, there you go!

EW:  Yeah, they was some of the first people &#8230; that&#8217;s the house that was built from that one tree.  [See discussion near 16:00.]  And uh &#8230;

Student:  That house is an historical landmark!

EW:  It&#8217;s over a hundred years old!  Um, they had a log house behind that one that they built first, and I don&#8217;t know whether mine was, where I was born was a log house or not &#8230; but my aunt was born there too, when they first came.

&#8212; 41:00m &#8212;

EW:  She was born there in, 1884, and I was born there in, 1915 &#8230; so, that house was (coughing) for a long time!

SS:  And were you a second generation, uh, Brutus community member, or &#8230; ?

EW:  Yeah, uh, third &#8230;

SS:  Third!

EW:  Yeah, my dad was born there, and I was born there.

SS:  So they came quite early?

EW:  Oh yeah, they came in &#8216;83.

SS:  1883?

EW:  Yeah, they bought that farm &#8230;

SS:  In 1883.

EW:  Yeah.

SS:  Which is only ten years after the first train went to Petoskey.

EW:  Yeah, ya - and on the Burgess side of the family, they came in, uh, let&#8217;s see - 1844.

SS:  Oh my god.

&#8212; 42:00m &#8212;

EW:  They came to, uh, southern Michigan &#8230; (to JT) what the heck was that?  (Unintelligible)  Woodstone, Woodland?  (laughs)  I couldn&#8217;t tell you where it is right now.  But, uh, then they came north in &#8216;76 - that was Kilpatricks at that time - he came north in 1876 - and, lived over winter, with an indian family in Cross Village, in a house that had no floor in it, a dirt floor.  And he went out to the, uh, the lake - Wycamp lake - and built a log house over winter, and then they moved out there in the spring.  And he was the first supervisor of Bliss township.

SS:  Oh, there you go - of Bliss?

EW:  Yeah.

&#8212; 43:00m &#8212;

Student:  Um, this has been on my mind for a while.  Earlier, didn&#8217;t you say that, um, the Mennonites, like, didn&#8217;t like the idea of people driving trucks, so they kicked them of the church or whatever?

EW:  Umm hmm.

Student:  Was it still like that when you were there?

EW:  Most of &#8216;em, most of &#8216;em was driving horses yet.  Uh, but it was just about that time, they changed, from a - (to JT) whatever they call &#8216;em - Mennonites out in &#8230;

JT:  Old order?

EW:  Yeah, the old order into the, newer order.  Then, when they started tractors they was glad to have (unintelligible) tractors!  (laughs)  Right now &#8230; but they, uh, they still wear their old &#8230;

JT:  Well, the old order people left.

EW:  Well, they didn&#8217;t really leave, but they just - died off.

JT:  (laughs)  Because Menno always talked about &#8230;

&#8212; 44:00m &#8212;

EW:  Well Menno was a younger &#8230;

JT:  Yeah.

EW:  He was a younger generation.

JT:  Yeah, he was the young generation, and he started going to that different church, up on the hill.

EW:  Yeah, well they went up there on the hill all the time.  That was the first church.

JT:  The old order was up there?

EW:  Oh yeah!

JT:  But then &#8230; ?

EW:  But, uh, his dad was the old order, and Harvey Brubaker was the new order.

SS:  (to students)  Write &#8216;Harvey Brubaker, old order&#8217; (laughs) &#8216;cause some of those names were mentioned in a book - (to EW) well, you&#8217;re in the book!  You&#8217;re in the book!

EW:  Yeah (laughs) - and, uh, oh gosh, they was Ebys, Brubakers, Burkharts, Gregorys, uh Martin &#8230; uh &#8230; gosh, they was &#8230; uh, there was quite a bunch of them there!

&#8212; 45:00m &#8212;

JT:  The Snyders?

EW:  Snyders!  Snyders was there.  His folks &#8230; uh, see my grandparents come over here in &#8216;83, and there was ten families come over at the same time as them.

SS:  And from where?

EW:  From Germany.

SS:  So that was a strong German &#8230;

EW:  Oh yeah, that was a German, well pretty-near all the Mennonites was German too.

JT:  Swiss-german.

EW:  Yeah.

SS:  That&#8217;s what I am!

(laughers)

EW:  Well, the Wursts was right in there close - Wurtzberg (?) is &#8230; right there.

SS:  Ooh!  Okay.

&#8212; 46:00m &#8212;

EW:  In fact, where Jason, er Kevin was, there, why it&#8217;s just up the valley, there, it goes right in to that.

JT:  Yeah, he&#8217;d gone up into the German part of Switzerland (unintelligible) - he took Jason up there, and they went camping up in the mountains.

(laughs)

EW:  Uh, they was, Wurst, and Clinks, and Kuglers, Shriers, uh, Kueblers &#8230;

SS:  Oh Kueblers, now is that the same Kiebler that&#8217;s in Petoskey?

EW:  Yeah.

SS:  K U E B L E R

EW:  Yeah, yeah.

SS:  I just wonder, &#8216;cause that&#8217;s the Kubler station, and they were over there, they ended up settling in Kegomic, actually.

EW:  Well, that was just Ed.

SS:  Okay.

EW:  That was one of the boys.

SS:  Oh, but the original ones &#8230;

EW:  He was the same age as my father was.

&#8212; 47:00m &#8212;

EW:  Yeah, and, uh, SYDOS.

SS:  And how do you spell SYDO?  S E Y?

JT:  S Y.

EW:  S E Y.

JT:  No, S Y.

EW:  Yeah, S Y.

[Not sure about the spelling of that name.]

EW:  And uh &#8230;

JT:  Buckhorns?

EW:  Yeah, well, the Buckhorns came later - they came in, uh, &#8216;bout &#8216;92.

SS:  1892?

EW:  1892.  This is, uh, this is the Ayr school &#8230; some pictures that the (unintelligible) brought down.  (to the schoolgirls) These are the kids that went to school, that school.

SS:  Ohh, so like, the enrollment.  Oh - (to students) see what that is?  And there&#8217;s the dates.

&#8212; 48:00m &#8212;

Students:  (murmuring)

SS:  Umm, unfortunately, the girls do have to get going pretty soon - I&#8217;ve got mothers coming - but this has been so much - and so enjoyable!  But I wanted to ask something, I&#8217;m very confused on something - maybe they (the schoolgirls) aren&#8217;t, but I am!  (laughs)  And that is the difference between Ayr, and Brutus?  Are they?

EW:  Just the distance.

SS:  But they&#8217;re two different communities?

EW:  Not really &#8230;

(JT protests)

EW:  They&#8217;re different communities, yeah, uh, but the Mennonites settled in Ayr first &#8230;

SS:  Oh, I see.

EW:  And then they built that church on top of the hill there.

SS:  Okay.

EW:  And they afterwards they moved out, and went over on the east side, and, uh, settled over there.

SS:  Which would be Brutus?

EW:  Yeah.

SS:  Okay.

&#8212; 49:00m &#8212;

JT:  That&#8217;s the Dam Site Inn, that&#8217;s where those people were.

EW:  Yeah.

SS:  That&#8217;s where most of Brutus &#8230; ?

EW:  Uh huh.

JT:  No, the Mennonites &#8230;

EW:  The Mennonites settled.

JT:  Are over there east of, the Dam Site Inn.

SS:  Okay (to students) - do you know where the Dam Site is?  Okay.  So east of that &#8230; so this book on Ayr Community School, where you&#8217;re listed as one of the sources, is something they could look at as Brutus?  Or &#8230;

EW:  Yeah, well, Maple River.

SS:  Maple River, &#8216;cause it says Maple River township, but then it has a Brutus telephone, and then there&#8217;s a map, and there&#8217;s Brutus, and then there&#8217;s Ayr &#8230; and so I was trying to establish for them, like the Brutus depot was specifically right in the heart of Brutus, and not what you would say was Ayr community.

EW:  Yeah, yeah, yeah.

JT:  When did the post office up here &#8230; when was it built, and when did it, uh, die?

&#8212; 50:00m &#8212;

EW:  I don&#8217;t know - it was nothing but a pile of logs when I first come up here, in &#8216;37, and I can&#8217;t ever remember - we was here - we collected cream in &#8216;27 - and I don&#8217;t remember the post office being there then, so, uh, the post office must have moved out, just before that.

SS:  And that post office would have been for Ayr.

EW:  Yeah.

SS:  Not Brutus?

EW:  Right.

SS:  Okay.  And then, there&#8217;s Ayr community school - would students from Brutus go to Ayr community school?  Or did they have their own school, Brutus school?

EW:  They had their own school, in Brutus.

SS:  In Brutus, ok.

&#8212; 51:00m &#8212;

EW:  And Ayr had, see Ayr, Ayr school was built in 19 &#8230; no 18, uh, &#8216;bout 1884 or five, I think &#8230; a woman lived where the Ayr cemetary is now, on that piece of property, and she started teaching kids there.  Before that, they had to go to the, uh, Pleasantview school, that was in, Tower and North Conway road.

SS:  Okay.

EW:  And uh, then when Ayr started up, why there was a lot of them, started going to Ayr school.  Uh, and they, I think it was only one year that they stayed in her house, that she had school in her house, and then they moved to, uh, the Ayr school started, Ayr school, and uh, that was in &#8230; that was a home, and then they built this other school in 1906.  So that school&#8217;s been there since 1906.

SS:  (to students) Well we talked a lot of (unintelligible).

Students:  (murmur)

SS:  This has been just wonderful - I think, the girls have gotten - you can see several pages of information!  (laughs)  And you were so generous to let us come, I wish we could stay longer!  Although we don&#8217;t want to wear out our welcome either.

&#8212; 52:00m &#8212;

EW:  Well, there&#8217;s some stuff about that &#8230; (unintelligible) uh, that you can take with you &#8230;

SS:  Oooh!

EW:  I don&#8217;t care, you can take &#8230; some more of that kind of stuff &#8230; that&#8217;s more about (unintelligible) &#8230; you can take some of the pictures, you can take all the pictures with you if you want &#8230;

SS:  &#8230; these are nice.

Student:  Are these ballteen?  [no idea what they&#8217;re talking about]

EW:  Yeah, those are ballteen, and uh &#8230;

SS:  Isn&#8217;t that fun?

SS:  Well, thank you!

Student:  Thank you so much!

EW:  That&#8217;s ok.  And this is, this is a map from Maple River so you can orientate yourself.

SS:  So all of it was Maple River, is that right?

EW:  Yeah.

SS:  All of it, so that&#8217;s why they &#8230; Maple River &#8230; clinic, so I thought &#8230; (unintelligible) the Maple River township!

EW:  There, that&#8217;s just about &#8230;

SS:  Is where that &#8230; clinic is?

&#8212; 53:00m &#8212;

EW:  Oh, well that&#8217;s a good boundary, that&#8217;s easy for me to &#8230;

JT:  Oh, the south boundary you mean?

EW:  Yeah.  And this road &#8230;

JT:  This corner down here is a four-township intersection.

SS:  Oohh!!

JT:  We&#8217;re in Pleasantview.

SS:  We&#8217;re in Pleasantview right now.

JT:  We&#8217;re in Pleasantview, south is Little Traverse, and east is Littlefield, and west is Maple River.

SS:  Oh boy, well &#8230;

&#8212; 53:35 TAPE RUNS OUT &#8212;


### I corresponded with Sally Smith to make sure she had no objections with putting this interview online

Kevin Trowbridge 06/08/09:

> Hi Mrs. Smith!
> 
> How are you these days?  I was in your class once upon a time (well, a
> long time ago now, I graduated in 1998!) and remember you well &#8230;
> 
> A few weeks ago my mother gave me a tape of an interview you organized
> with my grandpa Wurst back in 2002, about the history of Brutus.  I
> just wanted to let you know that I really enjoyed listening to it, and
> in fact I have transcribed it and placed it online, on my blog, so
> that I could share it with my cousins.
> 
> The blog post is at: http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/an-interview-with-elmer-g-wurst-brutus-michigan-from-1930-on
> 
> (And you can let me know having your conversation online bothers you
> at all, and I could take it down if necessary.  But the blog format is
> useful for sharing it with my family and there is much to be gained from
> making things like this public.
> 
> Grandpa passed away in 2004 and&#8212;well, we really loved him and miss
> him&#8212;so anything that reminds us of him, is extremely valuable to us.
> 
> I also enjoy the history of Northern Michigan a lot and I think it was
> an inspired project that you did, to help the youth to interview the
> local older people, and to document those interviews.  Training young
> people in the way of historians, to effectively interview their older
> relatives, is a very worthy project.
> 
> Thanks again, really, thanks a lot.  That tape was like pure gold for
> me.  And I learned a lot, it&#8217;s funny how sometimes it takes a stranger
> to ask the simplest questions &#8230; that your own relatives never think
> to ask.
> 
> Cheers,
> Kevin Trowbridge
> proud &#8216;Alanson Viking,&#8217; class of (nineteen) &#8216;98 ;)

Sally Smith 07/09/09:

> Dear Kevin,
> 
> It was so good to hear from you! Of course, I remember you.  I certainly enjoyed having you as a student.
> 
> I am so glad to hear that you and your family are still enjoying that tape of your grandfather&#8217;s interview. It was an 
> honor for the students and me to have had the opportunity to interview him.  He was an outstanding community leader 
> and a man of great character.  I do not have a problem with you sharing that tape with your family on your blog.
> I haven&#8217;t had a chance to visit the blog, but I will.
> 
> I thoroughly enjoy hearing from former students.  After all, I chose teaching as my career and hope to encourage 
> lifelong learning within them all.  I so appreciated your complimentary remarks regarding that project that we did.
> Your comments meant a lot.  Thank you. I am also pleased to hear that you enjoy Michigan history. I enjoy history as 
> well.  We learn so much from the culture of the past.
> 
> Let&#8217;s keep in touch.  Thanks again for your kind remarks. It is wonderful to hear from you!
> 
> Cheers to you, too, and happy summer.
> 
> Mrs. Smith
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
