<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Autobiographical | Kevin Trowbridge]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/blog/categories/autobiographical/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-03T12:38:24-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kevin Trowbridge]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[kevinmtrowbridge@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Breakers Blues Band]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2013-06-20-the-breakers-blues-band"/>
    <updated>2013-06-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/the-breakers-blues-band</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[## “Play that thing!”

My stage presence was lacking.  I wasn't confident, and it showed.  I hunched over the guitar and stared at my hands.
I didn't smile, or ever look at the audience.

![breakers blues band LIVE album cover](/assets//cd-cover-nutinis.jpg "Breakers Blues Band LIVE 
album cover.")

Suddenly, Big Ray pointed his huge, meaty finger at me and shouted: “Kevin! PLAY THAT THING!”  Unsatisfied, he grabbed a 
spare guitar, and waded in to save me.

Ray’s guitar playing was not technically very good.  He played very simply, perhaps one note in rhythm, bending the 
string.

But his was totally different, and BETTER, than my playing.  He stood tall, he radiated confidence, he got louder, he 
got quieter, he looked at the audience, he smiled, he walked around and interacted with the drummer, with the bassist.

… I was by far my own worst critic.  Not everyone in the audience is musical; many can’t tell when you play wrong notes.
If you are smiling, and moving with the rhythm of the song, and sounds are coming from your guitar, all seems well.

It’s insulting if people come to see you play, and you don’t attempt to give a convincing performance by smiling and 
having good stage presence.

As with many other things in life, fake it till you make it.

Here’s a recording of us LIVE at Michigan Tech in the fall of 2003: 

<iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/87125122&amp;color=ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false"></iframe>


## The Beginning

![a group shot of the band in Hancock, Michigan](/assets//finder.jpg &#8220;Posing on the shore of the 
Portage in Hancock, MI.&#8221;)

The genesis of the Breakers Blues Band was the Michigan Tech Jazz program, lead by talented and wonderful Mike Irish.

I played the trumpet in these bands all through college.  But honestly, I hated the trumpet.  The musician must match 
the instrument.  The trumpet was everything I was not: brassy, loud, and over-confident.

The guitar, on the other hand, was fundamental, a rhythm instrument, it hung out in the background, keeping time and 
sounding groovy.  Much more my speed.  And I had been secretly playing the guitar (and the keyboard) since back in high 
school.  I taught myself, from ”The Complete Easy Beatles” with simplified chord diagrams.

My trumpet hatred must have been obvious, because in the fall of 2003, there was an opening in the MTU Jazz band for a 
guitarist, and Mike Irish gave the spot to me.  Thus my escape from the trumpet was accomplished.

Soon afterwards, there were a series of ‘jam sessions’ at the Motherlode cafe in downtown Houghton, which I shyly 
attended, although I rarely played.

One night a strange and interesting guy showed up:

It was a typical scene&#8212;the cafe full of stereotypical engineering students: shy, pale, slight, quiet, introverted, no 
one talking. Suddenly a tall, large, bearded, joyous man, leapt onto the stage with his saxophone, and passionately 
played, many notes, up and down the scale, moving his body with the rhythm, totally dominating the stage.

It was kind of shocking!  Such a lack of reserve!  Such confidence!  Did we like it?  Not sure.  Did we notice? 
Definitely.

This was &#8220;Big Ray&#8221; Haywood, and shortly afterwards, he joined the MTU jazz band.

The charts we were playing were good practice, and very beautiful.  But they were played straight from the charts, and 
solos were generally short, and somewhat rehearsed.

So, the opportunity was definitely there for smaller groups to form.  But we were lacking id, or primal desire.  If you 
had asked me if I wanted to form a band and go around gigging at bars, the idea wouldn&#8217;t have appealed to me.  But I 
didn&#8217;t know what I was missing.  ;)

However, Ray had a passion for the blues!  He had already been in a band (the Crossroads Blues Band with his brother and 
others) back at home in Detroit, and here, he saw opportunity: music-making, and money-making potential.


## The Perks of Fame

My junior year of college, I spent in Switzerland, learning French.  It was so amazing, it reset all my expectations.
When I came back, I felt really down.  I didn&#8217;t want to be at Michigan Tech.  For almost two years, I limped along, not 
enjoying much, frustrated, apathetic.

The root problem was my poor attitude.  However, time cured me eventually: I just got tired of feeling down all the 
time, and I decided to live again, in the here and now, where I was.

The Breakers Blues Band was an important part of this new period of self-growth: I &#8220;came out of my shell.&#8221; We were 
successful.  We had groupies.  Our shows were always full: we regularly drew crowds of more than 100 people.

Also, I had a responsibility to pull my weight.  This included having a good stage presence by appearing to enjoy 
myself.  At first it was an act.  But slowly, it became real.

I switched to the keyboard: piano blues can be so simple.  I got a lot better.  I learned how to solo: start off softly, 
build tension with a repetitive note or a riff, and then build a vocabulary of little tricks that sound cool. Our whole 
group got tighter: we were aggressively gigging: 2 shows a week for more than a year.  It was a whole epoch of 
my life.

We even had away shows, in Marquette and Copper Harbor.  We would throw afterparties and invite our fans to party with 
us.  And, at one of these shows, I met my first real girlfriend: Mandy Edwards.

![the band posing with a true Detroit Bluesmobile](/assets//car.jpg &#8220;Posing in front of our vintage
Bluesmobile.&#8221;)

![playing at the Ramada Waterfront Inn in Hancock, Michigan](/assets//finder1.jpg &#8220;Playing a solo at 
the Ramada Waterfront Inn in Hancock, Michigan&#8221;)

![Ray Haywood, Alan Cross, and Kevin Trowbridge](/assets//haha.jpg &#8220;Three friends sharing a laugh
while setting up for a show.&#8221;)

![my first real girlfriend, Mandy Edwards](/assets//kevin_and_mandy.jpg &#8220;My first real girlfriend,
Mandy Edwards.&#8221;)]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving to San Francisco]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2013-04-09-moving-to-san-francisco"/>
    <updated>2013-04-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/moving-to-san-francisco</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[In all honesty, the time I spent in Mountain View was one of the most lonely and empty of my life. That sounds pretty 
dire, I wasn't depressed or sad, but the time was -- basically empty. When I thought about it later, I couldn't remember 
much happening.

I spent many nights at home alone, saving money, drinking "Full Sail Amber Ale," eating pasta, and watching films from 
[Ebert's Great Movies list](http://www.rogerebert.com/great-movies). ;)

![new housemates!](/assets//ian_gunn_kevin_trowbridge_alex_mayer_3656a_housewarming_party.jpg "Ian, me, and Alex Mayer at the 3656A housewarming party on October 6th, 2006.")

My dear friend Dan Simon came to visit me and he hated, hated, hated Mountain View. He paraphrased the poem [Slough by 
John Betjeman](http://www-cdr.stanford.edu/intuition/Slough.html):

> &#8220;Come friendly bombs and fall on Mountain View!
> It isn&#8217;t fit for humans now,
> &#8230;
> Tinned fruit, tinned meat, tinned milk, tinned beans,
> Tinned minds, tinned breath.&#8221;

So, in my weekly meetings with my manager Stephanie Schoch, I started speaking about how I would like to move to San 
Francisco. Moving to San Francisco was a constant tension amongst the young folks at Ariba and on the Peninsula. The 
glittering city was the allure, but the cost was having to commute more than an hour every morning and evening.

Stephanie encouraged me, so I started taking the Caltrain up to SF on weekends and at night to go to apartment open 
houses. At first I fell into a common trap: renting a studio in the TenderKnob. When I told Stephanie about this, she 
said: &#8220;You&#8217;re not living in some bullshit studio in the Tenderloin! You&#8217;re living in the Mission!&#8221;

![best buddies!](/assets//kevin_and_gatsby_trowbridge.jpg &#8220;Gatsby and I at the housewarming party.&#8221;)

So I decided that I wanted to move in with a group of housemates in a shared apartment in the Mission. I went to a few 
open houses, but they were so competitive, and I hated feeling judged or having to &#8220;sell myself&#8221; to potential roommates.

So, I came up with a new plan. I found a &#8220;Roommate Meetup&#8221; group where people seeking roommates could meet, in a bar, 
and try to connect. The people who were seeking a place to live, wore red nametags, and those who were seeking people to 
move in with them, wore blue nametags.

The first few times I went, I wore the red nametag, indicating that I didn&#8217;t have an apartment and I was looking for 
someplace to live. But, since we were drinking in a bar, there was a blurry line between socializing, and actually 
looking for someone to move in with. It wasn&#8217;t very efficient and it was still very competitive.

So I had a brainstorm: I could wear a blue tag, and &#8220;pretend&#8221; that I already had an apartment, but I would actually be 
looking for people to join me, in looking for an empty apartment, to &#8220;found&#8221; together.

This was the winning approach. At the next meetup, wearing the blue nametag, I started meeting people. It was a little 
embarrassing to admit that I didn&#8217;t actually have a place, but I stood out, and I met other ambitious people.

![ian gunn at 3656a&#8217;s housewarming party](/assets//ian_gunn.jpg &#8220;Ian at the 3656A housewarming party on October 8th, 2006.&#8221;)

One of these people was Ian Gunn. He had a job with Google directly out of college and he was living in corporate housing 
in Mountain View. At first I didn&#8217;t like him, he seemed young, and pushy. We talked for a few minutes and then moved on.

However, at the end of the night, just as I was contemplating the long, uncomfortable ride home on Caltrain, he 
approached me again, saying that he had a car and he would give me a ride back to Mountain View. I somewhat 
half-heartedly agreed.

But during the 45 minute car ride south, we started talking, and I realized that I really liked Ian Gunn. He was smart, 
and funny, and a good guy. We decided that we would be partners and look for an apartment together.

This was the beginning of an even more epic stage, which would be so boring to encyclopedically relate, but suffice it 
to say that we needed a 3rd roommate to join, who we found eventually: Alex Mayer. Using his skills with the ladies, 
Ian met a real estate agent, Tatianna, who eventually gave us the keys to a quasi-shitty apartment with a great 
location: 3656A 20th Street.

![san francisco skyline](/assets//3656a_back_porch_san_francisco_skyline.jpg &#8220;The view of SF downtown from 3656A&#8217;s back porch the night of the housewarming party.&#8221;)

Alex Mayer was gone in Thailand when we needed to sign the lease, so we called hotels in Thailand and faxed the 
documents to him there. On the night we needed him to actually sign the lease, he was gone on a 50 mile bike ride, and 
Ian and I found ourselves driving aimlessly around Palo Alto, because he had agreed to meet us at a certain place on 
the side of the road, at a certain time, to sign the lease. It was hilarious and very memorable.

But finally we were in! We got a place and we all moved in together on September 28th, 2006. It was one of the best 
decisions I had made in my life, thus far, because going forward, so many good things flowed from this.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
