<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Mexico | Kevin Trowbridge]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/blog/categories/mexico/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-03T12:18:27-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kevin Trowbridge]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[kevinmtrowbridge@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Note on the Cost of Living in Mexico]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2004-10-30-a-note-on-the-cost-of-living"/>
    <updated>2004-10-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/a-note-on-the-cost-of-living</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[The amount of money I am being paid here seems to me like a funny joke, and I of course didn't come to Mexico to become 
rich. It is a frustrating experience, however, not only to spend my savings to support myself here (while working my 
butt off from 9-5 each day), but also to witness the experience of the average Mexicans.

I am paid $4,800 pesos per month (the Mexicans use the same symbol, $, as we do to signify pesos), which seems to be 
average for an intern in Mexico. That equals $428 US per month, whereas as an intern in Minnesota last year I was 
earning about $2,500 per month (these figure are after taxes). In Mexico I am earning 17 % of what I earned in the US.

In Michigan people said to me, "Well, the prices are lower down there, aren't they?" I believed this to be so at the 
time, but distressingly in Monterrey the prices are not much lower than in the US.

For example let's consider a typical night out (prices in US dollars, assuming 11.25 pesos / dollar):

|                     | Mexico          | USA            |
| -------------       |---------------: | --------------:|
| Movie tickets       | $4              | $6.50          |
| Gasoline (1 gallon) | $2.26           | $1.80          |
| Dinner:             | $3.55 (tacos)   | $8 (hamburger) |
|                     | (2 beers) 4.44  | $6             |
| **Total**           | **$14.25**      | **$22.30**     |

<sub>
  * Mexican prices from my own experience and [this site](http://www.numbeo.com/cost-of-living/country_result.jsp?country=Mexico). 
  US prices from my experience.
</sub>

That puts the cost of the mexican night out at 63% that of the US night out. So my personal experience here is that I 
earn 80% less and spend 63% of what I would spend there!

There are mitigating factors. First we must acknowledge that what I am earning as an intern is not representative of 
the difference in wages between the two countries. In North America interns are paid well because they don&#8221;t usually 
live with their parents, have to move to a different city, own cars, etc. In Europe interns are often not paid anything 
as all! The Mexicans typically live with their families until they get married, and for this reason they can survive on 
lower wages and therefore they are paid lower wages.

However looking at official figures from the &#8220;CIA World Factbook&#8221; for 
[USA](http://www.cia.gov/cia/publications/factbook/geos/us.html) & [Mexico](http://www.cia.gov/cia/publications/factbook/geos/mx.html), 
it looks like my situation is, on the whole, representative of the difference in the cost of life between the US and 
Mexico.

|                 | Mexico          | USA            |
| &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;-   |&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;: | &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8211;:|
| GDP per capita  | $9k             | $37k           |

9k / 37k = Mexican GDP is 23% of the American GDP.

So to sum things up&#8212;if your costs were to decline proportionally with your earnings, it wouldn&#8217;t matter at all. But 
when your earnings drop dramatically while costs remain about the same, that just sucks! It translates into less 
economic freedom: you can&#8217;t do as many things, you can&#8217;t buy as much stuff, you can&#8217;t make as many trips&#8212;which makes 
it harder for you to become educated or dress well.]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A New Start]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2004-10-29-a-new-start"/>
    <updated>2004-10-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/a-new-start</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[My friend Theron Tingstad (see the [Just So Stories]() entry) has encouraged me 
to write more. He says that it will allow people to follow along with my experiences here in Mexico and to understand 
why I'm here.

People at home "not understanding" is in fact is one of the big frustrations when you spend time in another 
country. My exchange in Switzerland was one of the most fantastic experiences of my life, but when I returned to 
Michigan, the new ideas and ways of living that the trip generated just didn't seem to interest my friends and 
family very much.

C.S. Lewis once wrote to a small girl who had asked how to write:

> &#8230; instead of telling us a thing was &#8220;terrible,&#8221; describe it so that we&#8217;ll be terrified. 
> Don&#8217;t say it was delightful, make us say &#8220;delightful&#8221; when we&#8217;ve read the description. 
> You see, all those words (horrifying, wonderful, hideous, exquisite) are only like saying to your readers &#8220;Please 
> will you do my job for me.&#8221;

&#8212;From &#8220;Letter of 26 June 1956&#8221; 
[The Collected Letters of C. S. Lewis, Volume lll: Narnia, Cambridge, and Joy 1950-1963.](http://books.google.com/books?id=BCc6Aq5JaJoC&lpg=PA766&dq=%22Don&#8217;t%20say%20it%20was%20delightful%2C%20make%20us%20say%20%22delightful%22%20when%20we&#8217;ve%20read%20the%20description%22%20cs%20lewis&pg=PA766#v=onepage&q=%22Don&#8217;t%20say%20it%20was%20delightful,%20make%20us%20say%20%22delightful%22%20when%20we&#8217;ve%20read%20the%20description%22%20cs%20lewis&f=false)

So, let me show you what I mean by &#8220;friends and family weren&#8217;t interested.&#8221;

I loved the European way of socializing. In Switzerland it seemed that a cup of coffee or a bottle of wine could trigger 
hours of truly stimulating conversation&#8212;one of those core events when you seem to set foot on a higher plane of 
life, if only for a moment and you feel&#8212;this is what life is about, being here, now, with these people and 
communicating. These conversations are like when you read a truly good book and lose all sense of time, and when you 
finish it you feel like someone waking from a dream or splashing up from underwater.

In any case I became very fond of the tiny, tiny coffee cups, saucers, and spoons and the intimate ceremony of making 
coffee in an italian _macchina di caffè_ with the burner on low, snatching the coffee away just as the water boils, and, 
each time the same way, pouring in the spoonful of sugar and watching it dissolve, it that hypnotic way, as the 
conversation slowly warmed up to speed.

So I purchased an Italian coffee machine and a set of tiny, tiny coffee cups, saucers, and spoons, and tried to replicate 
the experience with my friends in Houghton, MI. My attempt to reproduce the &#8220;european feeling&#8221; in the US was 
a complete failure. To start off, my friends good-naturedly ribbed me about the dainty tableware. Americans are practical 
and use cups to drink from, not to create atmosphere. I realized that in the US we are incapable of that lavish, decadent 
use of time which the Europeans have down pat. My friends stood and watched while I prepared the coffee machine, checked 
their watches as the water heated, and once the coffee was poured, downed it in two big gulps and dashed off to do their 
homework. I was left in the kitchen with a coffee pot to clean and an unsatisfied desire to just have a really good talk 
with someone, anyone.

Then there was the christening party of our house in Houghton. I came back from Switzerland and moved directly in with 
four dear friends from the dormitories, so we were excited to invite everyone over to appreciate our new pad. I looked 
forward to sitting down with everyone and, civilly, pulling the cork on a bottle of wine and finding out their hopes, 
dreams, and the like. That was la mode in Switzerland, and I really enjoyed it. But Americans are raised in a very 
different &#8220;tradition.&#8221;

Since drinking is not legal until the citizen turns twenty-one, our social lives typically begin in fugitive style, 
drunken binges in the woods or in a house temporarily vacated by vacationing parents. Only in the most progressive of 
families would the parents introduce the children to alcohol or chaperone parties with alcohol, since providing drinks 
to minors is quite illegal and severely persecuted.

So I, after a year of comparatively civilized drinking in Lausanne, was shocked back into American reality when the 
guests to our party pooled, like children at an 8th grade dance, into separate groups of males and females, until, after 
half an hour of rapid imbibing, the social lubrication of the alcohol roared into effect and awkward silence was 
replaced by shouts, roars, keg-stands, and inevitably, vomiting. By one thirty everyone had stumbled off to bed. 
Conversation did not figure a major role in the evening.

So to come to a point (of which the lack of, in my stories, is frequently criticized), hopefully you, dear reader, can 
appreciate that things are different in foreign countries, and when you spend time abroad you grow to love those 
differences, and then, upon your return, you miss them, and it is quite hard to communicate what exactly it is that you 
miss, or why. That causes a lonely feeling which only time can dispel. I doubt my ability as a writer to communicate 
these cultural differences, but I have always wanted to give it a try.]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just So Stories]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2004-10-11-just-so-stories"/>
    <updated>2004-10-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/just-so-stories</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[I have just discovered that my good friend, Theron Tingstad of Lausanne, Switzerland fame, is in Cario, Egypt right now 
studying Arabic. No surprise to those of us who have followed his exploits in the past.

Go Theron! Continue the Michigan boy Hemingway tradition!

For the rest of you, follow his adventures at [Just So Stories.][1]

 [1]: http://ttjourney.blogspot.com/]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/2004-10-11-first-post"/>
    <updated>2004-10-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.kevinmtrowbridge.com/first-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Once again the task of writing something which masses of people will find interesting.

First, to introduce myself. I am Kevin Trowbridge.

\*handshake\* Hello, nice to meet you.

I am a 24 year old white American male engineer, currently in the midst of a 6-month "intercambio" (exchange)
in Monterrey, Mexico, working for the steel giant Hyslamex. I have managed to hang onto my old dream of becoming an 
international master of the universe / citizen of the world a la Einstein type &#8211; and this seemed to be a logical 
next step after graduating from college this Spring. So far my time here has not disappointed.

This blog is intended mostly for friends and family, but I will not hesitate to foray into more technical / opinions of 
the world type content which the general public might find to be interesting.]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
